<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pleasaunt disport of diuers noble personages: written in Italian by M. Iohn Bocace Florentine and poet laureat: in his boke vvhich is entituled Philocopo. And nowe Englished by H. G.</title>
            <title>Filocolo. English</title>
            <author>Boccaccio, Giovanni, 1313-1375.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1567</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110498</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846030</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10967</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10967)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 197:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pleasaunt disport of diuers noble personages: written in Italian by M. Iohn Bocace Florentine and poet laureat: in his boke vvhich is entituled Philocopo. And nowe Englished by H. G.</title>
                  <title>Filocolo. English</title>
                  <author>Boccaccio, Giovanni, 1313-1375.</author>
                  <author>Gifford, Humphrey.</author>
                  <author>Grantham, Henry, fl. 1571-1587.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2] 58 [i.e. 56] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Pater Noster Rowe, at the signe of the Marmayd, by H. Bynneman, for Richard Smyth and Nicholas England.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. 1567]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>H.G. = Humphrey Gifford or Henry Grantham.</note>
                  <note>Translation of: Filocolo.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from facsimile title page.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page cut affecting text; facsimile title page inserted previous to leaf 1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Italian fiction --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10967:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10967:1"/>
            <p>A pleaſaunt diſport of diuers Noble Perſonages. Written in Italian by M. IOHN BOCACE Florentine and Poet Laureat: in his Boke vvhich is entituled PHILOCOPO.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And nowe Engliſhed by H. G.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>OMNIA TEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PUS HABENT</head>
               <p>BE</p>
               <figDesc>blazon with a picture of a mermaid</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, in Pater Noſter Rowe, at the ſigne of the Marmayd, by H. Bynneman, for Richard Smyth and Nicholas England. ANNO DOMINI. 1567.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10967:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10967:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the right worshipfull M. William Rice Eſquire, H. G. wiſheth a happie long life, with increaſe of much Worſhippe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N HOW MVCH THE thankful ſorte are deſirous (as reaſon vvilleth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience daylie teacheth) to gratifie ſuche their deare friendes, as to vvhome for ſundrie good tournes and receyued benefits they are not a lyttle beholding, the ſundrie dealing of thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des daylie in vſe and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to the vvorlde, to the great prayſe and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation both of the one and the other gyueth a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimonie: So that, taking occaſion therby to ſhevv the good vvil I haue, to pay in part the debt many yeares due, for that your bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie tovvardes me (the leaſt ſparke vvhereof I am vnable to ſatiſfie:) I do giue vnto you this ITALIAN Diſporte, the vvhich I haue tourned out of his natiue attyre into this our ENGLISH habite, to the end the ſame maie b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no leſſe familiar to you and to ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (for your ſake) as ſhall vouchſafe thereof, than it is eyther to the ITALIAN or the FRENCH: and deſire that the ſame may march abrode vnder your charge: to vvhome I recoumpt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection therof. Not doubting but as the reading thereof ſhal bring pleaſure and delight: ſo the matter being thervvithall duely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſhall gyue ſundrie profitable Leſſons meete to be follovved. And bycauſe the name of the Author (being of no ſmal credit vvith the Learned, for thoſe his ſundry vvell vvritten vvorkes) is of it ſelfe ſufficient to carrie greater commendation therevvyth than my Pen
<pb facs="tcp:10967:3"/>
is able to write, I leaue to labour therin, leaſt my lacke may be an occaſion to the looſing of his due prayſe. And vntill Portune (the onely hope of the vnhappie) ſhal make me better able, I ſhal deſire you thankfully to accept this as a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and pledge of the good vvill I haue to performe that vvhervnto mine ability is vnable to ſtretch. Thus taking my leaue, I betake you to the tuitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of almighty God, vvho preſerue you in health to his pleaſure, and after this life make you poſſeſſor of thoſe ioyes vvhereof vve all hope to be partakers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Martij. 1566.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>The Booke to the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LOk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thou leape, dome not by viewe of face</l>
               <l>Leaſt haſt make waſt, in myſsedoming the caſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>For I teac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to Loue, ne yet his lore,</l>
               <l>Ne with what ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lue is cured ſuch a ſore:</l>
               <l>But I the carke with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ares that thereby happs,</l>
               <l>The blyſse with ioyes, the ſtorms with thunder clapps,</l>
               <l>The curteſies, where moſt his force is ſhewde,</l>
               <l>The choiſe of beſt, be it of good or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>de,</l>
               <l>Compare them ſo, as domed is the doubt</l>
               <l>Thereof, and aye the truth well ſifted ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>The which to reade ſuch pleaſure thou shalt finde</l>
               <l>As may content a well dyspoſed minde.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10967:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Prologue to the .xiii. Queſtions, compoſed in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, by M. Iohn Bocace, Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentine, and Poet Laureat: <hi>And nowe turned into Engliſh <hi>by H. G.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>LORIO</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Philocopo,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke <hi>Montorio, Aſcalion, Menedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>Maſſalino,</hi> in ſayling to ſéeke hys Friende <hi>Biancofiore,</hi> was thorow a very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and darke night, by the fierce winds, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen into gret dangers, but the perilles béeing once paſſed, they were caſt into the Porte of the auncient <hi>PARTHENOPE.</hi> whereas, of the Mariners (eſpying themſelues in Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) he receiued comfort, not knowing into what coaſt Fortune had forced him, yealded thankes to his Gods. And ſo tarried the newe day, the which after it once ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, the place was of the Mariners diſcried, ſo that they all glad of ſuretie &amp; of ſo acceptable arriuall, came a ſhoare. <hi>Philocopo</hi> with hys companions, who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſéemed to come forth new riſen againe out of their
<pb facs="tcp:10967:4"/>
Sepultures, than dyſbarked from ſhip, loked backe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the waywarde waters, and repeating in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the paſſed perilles of the ſpente night, coulde yet ſcarcely thinke themſelues in ſuretie. They all then with one voice prayſed their Goddes, that had guided them ſafe out of ſo crooked a courſe, offred their pitifull Sacrifices, and beganne to receyue comforte, and were by a friende of <hi>Aſcalions</hi> honorably receyued into the Citie, whereas they cauſed their Shippe to be all newe repaired and decked, of Maſt, Saile, and better Sterne than were the others which they had loſt: and ſo tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying time for their furder voyage, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which was much lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger lengthened than they loked for: by occaſion wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Philocopo</hi> would many times haue taken his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by land, but dyſcouraged therin by <hi>Aſcalion,</hi> ſtayed in tarrying a more proſperous houre in the aforeſayde place, where he and his companions ſawe <hi>Phebea</hi> fiue times rounde &amp; as many times ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned, before that <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> did abanden his violent forces. And in ſo long a while, they neuer almoſt ſawe time to be merrie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon <hi>Philocopo,</hi> who was very deſirous to performe his deferred iourney, one day called his companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and ſayd: Let vs go take the pleaſant aire, and paſſe the time vpon the ſalt ſea ſhoare in reaſoning and prouiding for our future voyage. Thus he, with the Duke <hi>Parmenion,</hi> and the reſt of his companions, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted their walke with a milde pace (diſcourſing diuers matters) towardes that place where reſt the reuerende Aſſhes of the moſt renoumed Peet <hi>Maro.</hi> They al thus talking a good ſpace, were not gone far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the City, but that they came to the ſide of a Garden, wherein they heard gracious &amp; ioyous feaſting of yong Gentlemen,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10967:4"/>
Dames, &amp; Damſels: There the aire dyd al reſounde with the noiſe of ſundrie inſtruments, and as it were of angelicall voices, entring with ſwéete delight into the hearts of them, to whoſe eares it came: the which noiſe it pleaſed <hi>Philocopo</hi> to ſtaie a while to heare, to the ende his former melancolie thorow the ſwéete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, might by little and little departe away. Then <hi>Aſcalion</hi> reſtrained their talke. And whileſt Fortune helde thus <hi>Philocopo</hi> and his companions without the garden intentiuely liſtening, a yong ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman comming forth thereof, eſpied them, &amp; forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with by ſight, porte and viſage, knew them to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gentlemen, &amp; worthie to be reuerenced. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he without tariaunce retourned to his companie and ſayde: Come, lette vs goe welcome certayne yong men ſéeming to be Gentlemen of great calling, the which perhaps baſhfull to enter herein not being bidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſtaie without, giuing eare to our dyſport. The companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s then of this Gentleman left their Ladies at their paſtime, &amp; went forth of the Garden, &amp; came to <hi>Philocopo,</hi> whom by ſight they knew to be chiefe of all the reſte, to whome they ſpake with that reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence their reaſon could deuiſe and that was moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for the welcomming of ſuch a gueſt, praying him that in honour and increaſe of this their Feaſt, it would pleaſe him and his companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to enter with them the Garden, conſtrayning him thorowe many requeſtes, that he ſhoulde in no wiſe denie them this curteſie. Theſe ſwéete prayers ſo pierced the gentle heart of <hi>Philocopo,</hi> and no leſſe the heartes of his companions, that he anſwered the intreators in this ſorte: Friends, of truth ſuch a Feaſt, was of vs nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:10967:5"/>
ſought for nor fled from, but like weather beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mates caſt into your Port, we to the ende to flie drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie thoughtes which ſpring of ydleneſſe, dyd in recy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our aduerſities, paſſe by theſe ſea banks: But howe Fortune hath allured vs to giue eare vnto you I know not, vnleſſe as we think, deſirous to remoue from vs all penſiueneſſe, ſhe hath of you, in whome I knowe to be infinite curteſy, made vs this offer: and therefore we will ſatiſfie your deſire, though peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in parte we become ſomewhat laueſſe of the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie which otherwiſe towardes others oughte to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede from vs. And thus talking, they entred toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Garden, whereas they founde manie faire Gentlewomen, of whome they were very graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly receyued, &amp; by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welcomed to their feaſt. After <hi>Philocopo</hi> had a good while behelde this their Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and likewiſe had feaſted with them, he thought it good to departe, and willing to take his leaue of the yong Gentlemen, and to gyue them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nkes for the honor he had receyued, one Lady more honorable tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt, indued with maruellous beautie and vertue, came forth where he ſtode, and thus ſayde vnto him: Moſt noble Sir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ye haue this morning thorowe this your great curteſie, ſhewed no ſmall pleaſure to theſe yong Gentlemen, for the which they ſhal be alwayes beholding vnto you, that is to wit, in that you haue vouchſafed to come to honor this our Feaſt. May it pleaſe you then not to refuſe to ſhewe vnto me &amp; to theſe other Dames, that fauor that I am ſecondarily to entreate you for: To whome <hi>Philocopo</hi> wyth a ſwéete voice aunſwered: Moſt gentle Lady, nothing may iuſtly be deuied you, commaunde therefore, for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:10967:5"/>
both I and theſe my companions are all preſt at your will: To whome the Lady ſayde in this wiſe: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as this your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming hath increaſed this our Feaſting, with a moſt noble and goodly companie, I ſhall deſire you that you wyll not wyth departure leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the ſame, but rather helpe vs here to ſpende thys day euen to the laſt houre, to that end we haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy begonne the ſame. <hi>Philocopo</hi> behelde hir in the face as ſhe thus ſpake, and ſeing hir eies replete with burning rayes to twinckle like vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning ſtar, and hir face exceding pleaſant and faire, thoughte ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to had ſéene (his <hi>Biancofiore</hi> excepted) ſo faire a creature: to whoſe demaund he thus made anſwere: Madame I ſhall diſpoſe my ſelf to ſatiſfie rather your deſire than mine owne, wherefore, ſo long as it ſhall pleaſe you, ſo long will I abide with you, &amp; theſe my companions alſo: The Lady gaue him greate than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and retourning to the others, bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne togethers with them all to be very merry. <hi>Philocopo</hi> abiding with them in this ſorte, entred gret familiaritie with a yong Gentleman named <hi>Galione,</hi> adorned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good qualities, and of a ſinguler eloquence, to whome in talking he ſayd thus: Oh, howe much are you more than any others beholding to the immortal Goddes, the which preſerue you quiet in one will in this your mirth making. We acknowledge vs to be greatly bounden vnto them, anſwered <hi>Galeone.</hi> But what occaſion moueth you to ſay this? <hi>Philocopo</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: Truely none other occaſion, but that I ſée you all here aſſembled in one will. Oh, ſayd <hi>Galeone,</hi> maruell not at all thereat, for this Lady in whom al excellencie doth reſte, both moueth vs herevnto, and
<pb facs="tcp:10967:6"/>
holdeth vs herein. Then demaunded <hi>Philocopo.</hi> And this Lady, who is ſhe? <hi>Galeone</hi> anſwered: It is ſhe that made requeſt vnto you that ye would tary here, when as a while ſince ye would haue departed. By ſyght ſhe ſéemeth vnto me (ſayde <hi>Philocopo</hi>) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding faire, and of a ſurmounting worthineſſe: but yet if my demaund be not vnléeful, manifeſt hir name vnto me, of whence ſhe is, and of what parentes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended. To whome <hi>Galeone</hi> anſwered: No wayes may your requeſt be vniuſt, byſides ther is none pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely talking of hir, which doeth not vouchſafe to publiſh the renoume of ſo worthy a Lady, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall fully ſatiſfie your demaund. Hir name is of vs here called <hi>Fiametta,</hi> howbeit the greateſt part of the people call hir by the name of hir, thorowe whome that wounde is ſhut vp, that the preuaricati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the firſt mother opened. She is the daughter of a moſt high Prince, vnder whoſe Scepter theſe Countreyes are quietly gouerned, ſhe is alſo Lady to vs all, and briefly, there is no vertue that ought to be in a noble heart, that is not in hirs. And as I thinke, in tarying this day with vs, you ſhall haue good expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience therof. That which you ſay (ſayd <hi>Philocopo</hi>) can not be hidden in hir ſemblance. The Gods guide hir, to that end that hir ſinguler gyftes do merite, for aſſuredly I beleue both that and much more than you haue affirmed. But theſe other dames, who are they? Theſe Gentlewomen (ſayde <hi>Galeone</hi>) ſome of them are of <hi>Parthenope,</hi> and other ſome of places elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, comen as are you your ſelues, hither into hir companie. And after they had thus helde talke a good ſpace, <hi>Galeone</hi> ſayd: Ah my ſwete friend, if it might
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10967:6"/>
not dyſpleaſe you, it ſhoulde be very acceptable vnto me to knowe further of your ſtate and condition, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your outwarde appearance repreſenteth, to the ende that by knowing you, we may do you that honor you worthily merite, bycauſe ſometimes want of knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge bringeth lacke of duetie to them that honoure others in not doing their due reuerence. To whome <hi>Philocopo</hi> aunſwered: No lacke in doing me reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence coulde any wayes happen on your behalfe, but rather ye haue therin ſo farre exceded, as with exceſſe ye haue paſſed the boundes and limits thereof. But ſince you deſire to knowe further of my condition, it ſhoulde be vniuſte not to ſatiſfie your deſire therein. And therefore (in how much it is léefull for me to dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer) I ſhal tel you: I am a poore Pilgrim of Loue, and goe ſéeking as ye ſée, a Lady of mine, taken away from me by ſubtile cautele by my Parents: and theſe Gentlemen whome ye ſée with me, of their curteſie kepe me companie in this my Pilgrimage: and my name is <hi>Philocopo</hi> of Nation a Spaniarde, driuen through tempeſtuous weather (ſéeking for the Iland of <hi>Cicilia</hi>) into your Portes. But he knew not ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertly to talke, as that the yong Gentleman vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode not more of his condition, than he willingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired he ſhoulde: and hauing compaſſion of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe his hard happes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſomewhat comforted him wyth wordes whych promyſed hym hereafter a more luckie lyfe, and from that tyme forwardes, to increaſe hys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, willed that he ſhould be honoured of them all, not as a Pilgrime or as a bydden gueſte, but rather as the chiefe and principall Patrone of the Feaſte. The Lady, who vnderſtode hys ſtate and condition,
<pb facs="tcp:10967:7"/>
through the reporte of <hi>Galeone,</hi> eſteming dearly of ſuch an hap, commaunded ſpecially that ſo it ſhuld be. <hi>Apollo</hi> was nowe with his Chariot of light moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Meridian circle, and dyd ſcarcely beholde with leueled eye, the newe apparelled earth, when as as theſe Dames, Damſels, and yong Gentlemen being thus aſſembled together in that place, (ſetting their feaſting apart) ſeking forth by ſundry quarters of the Garden the delightfull ſhade, and flying the noyſome heate that might offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their delicate bodies, toke by diuers companies, diuers delightes. And the Lady accompanied with foure others, toke <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo</hi> by the hande, ſaying: Sir, the heate doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine vs to ſéeke out the freſhe aire, let vs therefore go to yonder medow you ſée here before vs, and there with ſundry diſcourſes paſſe ouer the heate of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> day. <hi>Philocopo</hi> then greatly prayſed the Ladies deuiſe, &amp; followed hir motion, and with him his companions. <hi>Galeone</hi> alſo with two others, went with them to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> appointed medow, which was exceding faire of graſſe and floures, and filled with a ſwete ſuauitie of ſmels, about the which grew ſtore of yong trées very faire &amp; thicke of gréene leaues, wherewith the place was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended from the parching beames of the great Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. There was in the middeſt of that meddow a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Fountaine, very faire and cleare like Chriſtall, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the which they all ſate them downe, where ſome gazing in the water, &amp; other ſome gathering floures, they began to talke of ſundrie matters. But bicauſe ſometimes at vnwares the one did interrupt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> others tale, the faire Lady ſayde vnto them thus: To the rude that this our diſcourſe may procéede in a more
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10967:7"/>
better order, and ſo continue vntill the freſhe coole houres, the which we attend for our furder feaſting. Lette vs ordaine one of vs in place of our King, to whome eche one ſhal propound a Queſtion of Loue, and ſhall receyue from him an apte reſolution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: and truely (as I thinke) we ſhall no ſooner haue made an ende of oure Queſtions, but that the heate (we not knowing howe) ſhall be paſte, and the tyme ſpent to our profite and delight. This deuiſe pleaſed them all, and among them it was ſayd: Let there be a King: and with one voice they al choſe <hi>Aſcalion</hi> to their King, for that he was ſome what more growen in yeares than was any of the reſt: To whome hée made aunſwere, to bée altogether inſufficiente for ſo great an office, bycauſe he had ſpent moeyeres in the ſeruice of <hi>Mars,</hi> than of <hi>Venus.</hi> But yet he prayed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al to leaue vnto him ſhe Election of ſuch a King. They that thought him to be ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne (knowing ſo well before hand the qualities of them all) as would conſtitute one ſuch, as ſhould yelde true aunſwere to al their demaundes, did then wholly conſent that the Election ſhould fréely be remitted vnto him, ſince he would not take ſuch a dignitie vpon himſelfe. <hi>Aſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> then roſe hym vp, &amp; gathered certayne twygges<note place="margin">Fiametta choſen quene to define the questions propounded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> of a gréene Laurell, the ſhade whereof dyd ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the freſhe Fountaine, and thereof made a rich Coronet, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which he brought in preſence of them all, and ſayde in this wyſe: From the time that I in my moſt youth full yeares began to haue vnderſtanding, I ſwere by thoſe Gods whome I worſhip, that I do not remember to haue ſéene or heard named, a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of like worthineſſe to <hi>Fiametta,</hi> of whome Loue
<pb facs="tcp:10967:8"/>
holdeth vs all here in hir preſence inflamed, and by whome we haue this day bene honoured in ſuch ſort, as we ought neuer to forgette the ſame. And bycauſe ſhe (as wythout doubt I know) is plentifully endued with euery good grace, adorned both w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beautie &amp; good qualities, &amp; endued with a flowing eloquence, I ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make choiſe of hir to be our Quéene. For aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly it is conuenient that the Imperiall Crowne be beſtowed vpon hir magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, being diſcended from a ſtirpe royall, to whome the ſecret wayes of Loue, being (as they are al) open, it ſhall be an eaſie matter for hir to content vs in theſe our Queſtions. And this ſayde, he humbly knéeled before this noble Lady ſaying: Moſt curteous Lady vouchſafe to deck your heade with this Crowne, the which is no leſſe dearly to be eſtéemed of them, that are worthy thorow their vertues to couer their heades with the like, than if it were of Golde. The Lady with a newe r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hir white viſage, and ſayd: Truly ye haue not in due ſorte prouided a Quene for this amorous people, (that haue more néede of a moſt able King) for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> of al you that are preſent, I am the moſt ſimple &amp; of leaſt vertue, neyther is there any one of you y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is not more mete to be inueſted of ſuch a crowne than am I. But ſince it thus pleaſeth you, I can not withſtande thys your Election: and to the ende I be not founde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our made promiſſe, I will receyue it, and as I hope ſhal eke receiue from the Gods with it, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke due to ſuch an office: and thorow the help of him to whom theſe leaues were alwayes acceptable, I ſhall anſwere you all, according to my ſmall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: Neuertheleſſe, I deuoutely pray him that he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10967:8"/>
wil enter into my breaſt, and renewe my voice wyth that ſounde wherewith be cauſed the valiante van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed man <hi>Marſia,</hi> to deſerue to be drawen forth of the ſheath of his members. I by way of mirth ſhal giue you lyght aunſweres without ſyfting to the depth of your propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Queſtions, the going about to ſearch forth the which, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uld rather bring tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe than delight to your mindes. And hauing thus ſayde, ſhe toke with hir delicate hand the offred Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and therewithall crowned hir heade, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that ech one vpon payne to be depriued of the amorous ioyes, ſhould prepare to put forth ſome que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the which might be apte and conuenient to the purpoſe whereof they did intende to entreate, &amp; ſuch a one as ſhould rather be an increaſer of their mirth than thorough too greate ſubtiltie, or otherwiſe, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of the ſame.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The firſt Queſtion, propoſed by PHILOCOPO.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the right hande of ſhe Quéene ſat <hi>Philocopo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Quene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth Philocopo to propound.</note> to whome ſhée ſayde: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sir, you ſhall begin to propounde your Queſtion, to the ende that the reſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, as we are here placed, maye after you, with more ſuertie propounde theirs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. To whom <hi>Philocopo</hi> thus made anſwere: Moſt
<pb facs="tcp:10967:9"/>
noble Lady, without my forſlowing, I ſhall obey your commaundement, and thus ſayd: I remember that in the Citie, wherin I was borne, there was one day made a bountifull great Feaſt, whera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to honor the ſame, were many Gentlemen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gentlewomen: And I that was likewiſe there roming about, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding<note place="margin">Two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men enamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of one Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> them that were in the place, eſpied among y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> reſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. yong men very gracious to behold, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> earneſtly eyed an excéeding faire yong woman. Neither was I any ways able to diſcerne whether of them hir beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie had moſt inflamed. And as ſhe in like ſorte had a good ſpace beheld them, not making greater ſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the one than to the other, they betwene themſelues began to reaſon of hir: and among the other wordes that I vnderſtoode of their talke, was that eche one ſayde, that hée was hir beſt beloued: and for proofe thereof, either of them alleaged in the furtherance of himſelf, diuers geſtures then before done by the yong woman. And they thus remaining in this conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a long time, being now thorowe many words at daggers drawing, they acknowledged, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> herein they did very euill, bicauſe in thus doing, they wrought hurt and ſhame to them ſelues, and diſpleaſure to the woman. Wherfore (moued of an equall agréement) both two went to the mother of the maide, who was alſo at the ſame Feaſt, and thus ſayd vnto hir: That forſomuch as aboue all other women of the worlde, either of them beſt liked hir daughter, and that they were at contention whether of them was beſt liked of hir, it would therefore pleaſe hir to graunt them this fauour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the end no greater inconuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce might ſpring therof, as to will hir daughter, that ſhe either
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:10967:9"/>
by worde or déede, would ſhewe whether of them ſheſ beſt loued. The intreated Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ling, thus aunſwered: Willingly. And ſo calling hir daughter to hir, ſayd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> My <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> daughter, eche one of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth the loue of thée aboue the loue of himſelfe, &amp; in this contention they are: whether of them is beſt beloued of thée: and they ſéeke of me this fauour, that thou either by ſignes or words, reſolue them herein.<note place="margin">Wher as loue is, ther peace ought to be.</note> And therefore to the end that Loue, from whome all peace and goodneſſe ought alwayes to ſpring, bréede not now the contrary, content them in this, and with ſemblable curteſie, ſhew towardes which of them thy mynde is moſt bent. The yong damſell ſayd: It li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mée right well. And ſo beholding them both a while, ſhe ſaw the one of them to haue vpon his head<note place="margin">The Loued giueth cauſe of argument to hir louers.</note> a faire garlande of freſh floures, and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other to ſtand without any garlande at all. Then ſhe that had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vpon hir head a garlande of gréene leaues, firſt tooke the ſame from hir head, and ſet it vpon his, that ſtode before hir without a garland. And after ſhe toke that which y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other yong man had vpon his head, and ſet the ſame vpon hirs: and ſo leauing them, ſhée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Feaſt, ſaying that ſhe had both perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the commaundement of hir mother, as eke their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſire. The yong men being thus left, returned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to their former contention, ech one affirming that ſhe loued him beſt. And he whoſe garlande ſhée tooke and ſet vpon hir head, ſayde: Aſſuredly ſhe loueth me beſt, bicauſe ſhe hath taken my garland to none other ende, but for that what myne is, pleaſeth hir, and to giue occaſion to bée beholding vnto me. But to thée, ſhe hath giuen hirs, as it were in place of hir laſt fare
<pb facs="tcp:10967:10"/>
well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vnwilling that (like a countrey girle) the loue which thou bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hir, be without requital, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore laſtly ſhe giueth thee that garlande thou haddeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> her replying with the contrary, thus anſwered: Truly ſheloweth that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hine is, better than thée, and that may be ſene in taking therof. And me ſhe loueth better than what myne is, in as muche as ſhe hath gyuen me of hirs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And therefore it is no to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of hir laſt deſerued gift, as thou affirmeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a beginning of amitie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d loue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A gifte maketh the receiuer a ſubiecte to the giuer: and bicauſe ſhée p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aduenture vncertaine of me, to the ende ſhe might be more certaine to haue me hir ſubiect, wil binde me (i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perhap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were not bounde vnto hir before) to bée hirs by gift. But how mayſt thou thinke, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he at the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake away from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer ſhe may vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to giue thée and thus they abode a long time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, and in the end departed without any defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all. Now ſay I moſt puiſſant Quéene, if you ſhoulde bée demaunded of the laſte ſentence of ſuch a contention, what woulde ye iudge. The faire La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſomewhat ſmiling, turned towardes <hi>Philocopo,</hi> (hir eyes ſpark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing with an amorous light) and after a ſoft ſigh, thus made anſwere: Moſt noble youth;<note place="margin">The Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the queſtion.</note> proper is your queſtion: And truely, as very wiſely the yong woman behaued hir ſelfe, ſo eche one of the yong men right well defended his cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But bicauſe ye require what we laſtly will iudge therof, thus we make you anſwere: It ſéemeth vnto vs, &amp; ſo it ought to ſéeme to eche one that taketh good héede, that the woman had in hate neither y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> one nor the other: but to kéepe hir intent couert dyd two contrary actes, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10967:10"/>
apeareth, and not without occaſion. And to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> end ſhe might get more aſſured the loue of him whom ſhe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as not to loſe the loue of the other, whom ſhe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not, it was but wiſely done. But to come to our Queſtion, which is, to whether of the two greateſt loue was ſhewed. We ſaye: that ſhe loued him beſt and he chiefeſt in hir fauour, to whome ſhée gaue hir garlande: and this ſéemeth to be the reaſon: What ſo euer man or woman that loueth any perſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eche one thorowe force of the loue they heare, is ſo ſtrongly bound to the perſon loued, that aboue al other things they deſire to pleaſe the ſame, neither to bynde him or hir more ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly that thus loueth, néedeth either gifts or ſeruices, and this is manifeſt. And yet we ſée, that who ſo loueth, though he endeuour him ſelfe ſundry wayes, is not able to make the perſon loued, in any ſorte benigne and ſubiect vnto hym, whereby he may bryng it to his pleaſure, and ſo with a more hold face demaunde his deſire. And that this is in ſuche ſorte as we ſay, the inflamed <hi>Dido</hi> with hir doings, doth<note place="margin">Dido.</note> very well manifeſt the ſame vnto vs, who burning in the loue of <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſo long as it ſéemed hir neither<note place="margin">Aeneas.</note> with honours nor with gifts able to winne him, had not the courage to attempt the doubtfull waye of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the queſtion: So that then the yong woman ſought to make him moſt beholding vnto hir, whom ſhe beſt loued. And thus we ſay, that he that re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the gift of the Garlande, was hir beſt beloued. As the Quéene become ſilent, <hi>Philocopo</hi> anſwered: Diſcrete Lady, greatly is your anſwere to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:<note place="margin">Philocopo replieth to the Quene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but for all that, you doe bring me into a greate admiration of that ye haue defined, touching the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10967:11"/>
queſtion, bycauſe I woulde haue iudged ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the contrary. For ſo much as generally among louers, this was the wont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d cuſtome, that is, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vppon them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iewell, or ſome other thing of the perſons loued, to thende that moſt times they might glorie themſelues more therein, than in all the remnant they had, and perceiuing the ſame aboute them, therewith to glad their mindes, as ye<note place="margin">Paris.</note> haue hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Parys</hi> ſeldome times or neuer entred into the bloud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e battailes againſt the Gréekes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bearing ſome token vpon him, that had ben gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by his <hi>Helene,</hi> beleuing better to preuaile<note place="margin">Helen.</note> therwith, than if he had gone without the ſame. And truely in my opinion, his thoughte was not vaine: therfore I ſhoulde thus ſay, that (as you ſayde) the yong woman did very wyſely, not defining it for all that as you haue done, but in this maner: She kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe was very wel loued of two yongmen, and that ſhe coulde not loue moe than one, for that Loue is an indeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>e thing, ſhe would rewarde the one for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he loue he bare hir, to the end that ſuch good will ſhould not be vnrewarded, and ſo gaue him hir Garland in requitall therof. To the other whom ſhe loued, ſhe thought ſhe would giue courage and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hope of hir loue, taking his Garlande, and dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hir ſelfe therwith, in token wherof, ſhe plainly ſhewed to be beholding vnto him for the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And therfore in my Iudgement ſhe loued better him from<note place="margin">The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſolution of this first question.</note> whom ſhe toke, than him to whom ſhe gaue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to whom the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>us made aunſwere: Youre argument ſhould haue pleaſed vs right wel, if your ſelf in your tale had no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> condemned the ſame. Sée howe pillage
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10967:11"/>
and perfect loue can agrée together? How can ye ſhew me, that we loue him whome we ſpoile, better than him, to whome we giue? According to the Queſtion propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, to the one ſhe gaue a Garland, and from the other ſhe tooke a Garland: neyther had ſhe from whom ſhe gaue, ought giuen hir: and that which we ſée euery day for example may here ſuffiſe, as is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſayde. They are of Gentlemen farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loued, on whome they beſtowe fauor and giftes, than thoſe that are by them depriued of them. And for that cauſe we laſtely holde opinion, concluding that he is better loued, to whome is giuen, than hée from whome is taken. We know very well, that in theſe our reaſonings much might be obiected againſt this oure definition, and much alſo aunſwered to the contrary reaſons: But laſtly ſuch determination ſhall remaine true. And bicauſe time now ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not, to ſtay with this our talke vpon one matter only without moe, we will giue eare to the reſt if it pleaſe you. To whome <hi>Philocopo</hi> ſayde: That it pleaſed him right wel, &amp; that very well ſuffiſed ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded queſtion: &amp; ſo helde his peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10967:12"/>
               <head>¶ The ſecond Queſtion, propoſed by LONGANO.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext to <hi>Philocopo</hi> was placed a curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous yong man, and gracious to behold, whoſe Name was <hi>Longano,</hi> who no ſooner than <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo</hi> had left, thus began: Moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Quéene, ſo trim hath bene the firſte queſtion, that in my conceipt, myne ſhall bring no delight at all. Yet to the ende not to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from ſo noble a company, forth it ſhal: &amp; thus he folowed, ſaying: It is not many dayes paſt, that I abyding all ſolitarie in my chaumber, wrapte in a heape of troubleſome thoughtes, ſprong from an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous deſire, the which with a fierce battaile had aſſaulted my heart, by happe heard a pitious plaint,<note place="margin">Two ſiſters complaine them of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in loue.</note> wherevnto (bycauſe I iudged it by eſtimation néere vnto me) intentiuely I layde myne eare, and therby knew that they were women: by occaſion wherof, I ſodainly roſe to ſée who, and where they were: and loking forth at my chaumber window, I heard o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt the ſame, in one other chaumber, two yong women, the ſame being ſiſters, adorned with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable beautie, there abiding without any other companie, whome as I ſawe making this ſorowfull plaint, I withdrew my ſelfe into a ſecret place, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10967:12"/>
being of them eſpied, and ſo beheld them a long while, neither was I able for all that, to vnderſtand all the wordes that they thorowe griefe vttered in teares, but that the effect of ſuch plaint (according to that I coulde comprehende) ſéemed to mée to be for Loue: wherefore I thorowe pitie, and ſo ſwéete an occaſion offred (beyng thus cloſe as I was) began to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heade my trickeling teares. And after that I had in their griefe perſeuered in the ſame a good ſpace (for ſomuch as I was their very familiar and alſo their néere kinſman) I purpoſed to vnderſtande more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the occaſion of their ſorrowe, and ſo went vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who had no ſooner eſpied me, but al baſheful they withheld them from teares, endeuoring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to do me reuerence. To whom I ſayd: Gentlewomen, trouble not your ſelues, neyther let this my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming moue you to reſtraine your inward griefe, for your teares haue ben now a good ſpace apparant vnto me. It ſhall bée therfore néedeleſſe to hide you, either yet thorowe baſhefulneſſe to hide from me the cauſe of this your plaint. For I am come hither to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſame. And be you aſſured, that ye ſhal not receiue by me either in word or déede any euil requital. But rather helpe and comfort in what I maye. The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men greately excuſed them ſelues, ſaying, that they ſorrowed for nothing: but yet after I had coniured them, and they ſeyng me deſirous to vnderſtande the ſame, the elder thus began to ſay: It is the pleaſure of the Gods, that to thée our ſecretes be diſcouered: thou therfore ſhalt vnderſtande, that wée, aboue all other women haue alwayes reſiſted the ſharp dartes of <hi>Cupide,</hi> who of a long ſeaſon in caſting y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:10967:13"/>
was neuer yet able to faſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nrher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. But now laſtly being further inflamed, &amp; hauing determined to ouercome that his childiſh enterpriſe, tooke of new with his yong arme, of his beſt &amp; deareſt ſhafts, &amp; with ſo great force wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hearts ſo ſore inféebled through the ſundry blowes before receiued, as the heades therof pierced déepe, ſo as they made a farre greatter wounde, than if reſiſtance had not ben made (to the other former) had lyke to haue bene. And thus for the pleaſure of two moſt noble yong Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we are become ſubiects to his deitie, folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing his pleaſure with more perfect faith, and ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t will, than euer any other women haue done. Now hath Fortune, &amp; the loue of them (as I ſhall declare vnto you) lefte vs both comfortleſſe. Firſt I, before<note place="margin">The firſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth the loſſe of hir enioied louer</note> my ſiſter here, was in loue, and through myne ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor beleuing wiſely to end my deſire, ſo wrought as I got the loued yong Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at my pleaſure, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I found as greatly enamoured of me as I of hym. But truly now hath not the amorous flame through ſuch effect ceſſed, neither hath the deſire leſſned, but eache one more veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly increaſeth: and more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer, I do now burne in his fire. And what tyme, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how I might beſt mitigate the flame therof, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it inwardly ſecrete, it after happened, that the horned Moone was no ſooner come to hir perfect rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d neſſe, but that he at vnwares co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted a fault, for the which was adiudged him perpetuall exile from this Citie, whervpon he dreading death, is departed he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re without hope euer to returne. I ſorowfull woman aboue all others, more now inflamed than euer, am without him, left both dolefull and deſperate. By oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10967:13"/>
wherof I ſorrow me, and that thing that moſt increaſeth my ſorrow is, that on euery ſide I ſée the way hard from being able to folow him. Think ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now, whether I haue cauſe to plaine me or no. Then ſayde I: and this other, why ſorroweth ſhe?<note place="margin">The ſeconde hindred by ielouſie, ſoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth hir hap</note> and ſhe anſwered: This my ſiſter likewiſe (as I) is enamoured of an other, and of him againe loued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue meaſure. And to the ende her deſires ſhould not paſſe the amorous pathes, without taſting ſome part of delight, many times ſhe hath endeuoured hir ſelfe to bring them to effecte, and contrary to hir deuiſe, Iealouſy hath alwais occupied and broken the way, and bicauſe ſhe could neuer attain thervnto, neither ſawe howe to be able ſo to do, ſhée thus diſtreſſed, is thorow feruent loue conſumed, as ye may wel think if euer ye were in loue. Seing we were then here all alone, we began to reaſon of oure miſfortunes, and knowing the ſame farre greater than theſe of other wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we could not withhold from teares, but with wéeping ſorowed our luckleſſe lots, as ye might wel perceiue. To heare this of them it grieued me great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo that I encountred them with ſuch wordes, as ſéemed me moſt profitable for their comforte, &amp; ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Many times after, reuoluing in mynd their griefs, and ſomtimes bethinkyng me whether of the ſame ſhuld be the greater, at one time I agréed to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> of the one, &amp; at another time I yelded to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> of the other: &amp; the ſundry reaſons, wherewith as it ſéemeth me, eche one hath to lamente hir, will not ſuffer me to ſtay vpon any one, wherevpon I remaine here in doubt. May it therefore pleaſe you, that by you may be opened this errour, in telling me whether of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:10967:14"/>
two infortunate louers ſéemed to ſuſtaine the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt griefe. Great was the ſorrow of either of them,<note place="margin">The Quene decideth the question.</note> aunſwered the Quéene: But conſidering aduerſitie to be moſt grieuous to hir that hath taſted proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, we eſteeme that ſhe that hath loſt hir loue, féeleth the greateſt griefe, and is of Fortune greatlieſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. <hi>Fabritius</hi> neuer bewept the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune:<note place="margin">Fabritius. Pompey. Medea. Iaſon.</note> But that <hi>Pompey</hi> did is a thing very mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. If ſwéete things were not taſted, the ſowre ſhuld be yet vnknowen. <hi>Medea</hi> neuer knewe (according to hir own ſaying) what maner a thing proſperity was, whileſt ſhe was in loue, but beyng forſaken of <hi>Iaſon</hi> bewailed hir aduerſitie. Who will euer lament for that he hath not had? not one but will rather deſire<note place="margin">Longano of contrary opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to the Quene.</note> it. It is déemed therefore, that of the two women, the one wept for griefe, the other for deſire. It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard for me (gracious Lady) to thinke that which you affirme (ſayde the yong Gentleman) forſomuch as who y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hath his deſire of any deſired thing, ought much more to content his mynde, than who that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth, and can not fulfill his deſire. Further, nothing is more light to loſe, than what hope promiſeth not hereafter to yelde. There ought to be vnmeaſurable grief, where as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> not being able to bring egal willes to effect doth hinder. From thence lamentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s take place, from thence thoughts and troubles do ſpring, bicauſe if the willes were not egall, of force the deſire ſhould want. But when as louers ſée them ſelues in preſence of that they deſire, and can not attaine ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, then do they kindle &amp; ſorrow them much more, than if that they would haue, were farre from them.<note place="margin">Tantalus.</note> And who I pray you torments <hi>Tantalus</hi> in Hel? but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10967:14"/>
onely the Apples, and the Water, for that how much more néere they bende &amp; ſwell to his mouth, ſo much the more (afterwardes in flying the ſame) they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his hunger. Truly I beleue, that who hopeth for a thing poſſible to bée had, &amp; can not attaine ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, thorowe contrary reſiſting impedimentes, fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth more griefe, than who that bewaileth a thing loſte and irrecuperable. Then ſayde the Quéene,<note place="margin">The Quenes ſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. queſtion.</note> your anſwere woulde haue folowed very well, where youre demaunde ſhould haue bene of an olde griefe, although to that alſo might be ſaid: thus to be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thorowe forgetting the griefe, to ſhorten the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in the deſired things, where as continuall impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment is ſéene not to be able to attaine them, as in thoſe loſt, wherin Hope doth not ſhewe vs, that wée ſhoulde euer haue them againe. But wée doe reaſon whether of them ſorrowed moſt, when you ſaw them ſorrowing: wherfore folowing the propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded caſe, we wil giue iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that ſhe felt greater grief that had loſt hir louer, without hope to haue hym againe, (putting the caſe that it be an eaſye matter to loſe a thing impoſſible to haue agayne: neuertheleſſe it was to be ſayde: who loueth well, forgetteth neuer) than the other, who if we loke well, might hope to fulfill that hereafter, that heretofore ſhe was vnable to performe. For a greate leſſner of griefe is hope. It had force to kepe chaſt and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the ſorrowes of the lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gryng long lyfe of <hi>Penelope.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10967:15"/>
               <head>¶ The thirde Queſtion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by a yong Gentlewoman.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the right ſyde of <hi>Longano</hi> ſate an excellent faire Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman and verie pleaſant, who as ſhe perceiued that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion by the Quéene determined, thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne with a ſwéete talke to ſay: Moſt renoumed Quéene, your eares graunte hearing to my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: And firſt by thoſe Goddes whome you worſhip, and next by the power of our paſtime, I pray you that ye will giue to my demaund profitable counſell. I as you know, being deſcended of noble Parentes, was borne in this City, and was named with a very gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious name, although my ſurname (being <hi>Cara</hi>) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth me grateful to the hearers, and as by my face it may appeare, I haue receyued from the Gods and Nature a ſinguler gift of beautie, the which (in folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing my propre name more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſurname) I haue adorned with an infinite pleaſauntneſſe, ſhewing my ſelfe benigne to whom that is delighted to behold the ſame: by occaſion whereof many haue endeuoured themſelues for their pleaſure to occupie my eyes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt al whom I haue withſtode w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtrong reſiſtance holding a ſtable heart agaynſt their aſſaultes: but bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſéemeth to me vnléefull that I onely ſhoulde
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10967:15"/>
pretermit the lawes kept and obſerued of all others,<note place="margin">The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought ſonest to be loued, eyther the Strong<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Liberal, or the Wiſe.</note> that is, not to loue being loued of many, I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to become enamored, and ſetting apart ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſéekers of ſuch loue, whereof ſome do excell <hi>Midas</hi> in riches, ſome other paſſe <hi>Abſalo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> in beauty, &amp; other ſome in curteſie (according to the common reporte of all) are more ſplendent than any other. I haue of al theſe choſen thrée: Of whom eche one pleaſeth me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. Of the which thrée, the one of bodily force (as I beleue) would excell the good <hi>Hector,</hi> hée is at euery proofe ſo vigorous and ſtrong. The curteſie and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of the ſeconde is ſuch, that (as I thinke) his fame doth ſounde thorowe eche pole. The third is al full of wiſedome, ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he ſurmounteth all other wiſe men aboue meaſure. But for that (as ye haue heard) their qualities are diuers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I doubt whether of them to take, finding in the antique age ech one of theſe to haue diuerſly the courages of women, and of yelding men: as of <hi>Dianira, Hercules,</hi> of our <hi>Clitemneſtra, Aegiſtus,</hi> and of <hi>Lucretia, Sextus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Counſel me ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to whether of them ſoneſt with leaſt blame, and greateſt ſuretie I ought to giue my ſelfe. The plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Quéene hauing heard the purpoſe of this Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman,<note place="margin">The queenes aunſwere.</note> thus made anſwere. There is neuer a one of the thrée, that doth not worthily merite the loue of a faire and gracious Lady: but bicauſe in this caſe I am not to fight againſt Caſtels, or to giue away the kingdomes of greate <hi>Alexander,</hi> or the treaſures of <hi>Ptholome,</hi> but that only that Leue and Honour are with diſcretion a long time to be kept, the which are maintained neither by force nor curteſy, but onely by wiſedome: We ſay, that both you, and euery other
<pb facs="tcp:10967:16"/>
woman ought rather to giue hir loue to a wiſe man,<note place="margin">The reply of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman.</note> than to any of the reſt. Oh how diuers is my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from yours, anſwered the propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman. To me it ſéemeth, that eche one of the others were ſooner to be taken than the wiſe, &amp; this ſéemeth to be the reaſon: Loue (as we ſée) is of that nature, as multiplying his force in one hearte, euery other thing he baniſheth out thence, retaining that for hys ſeate, and mouing it after according to his pleaſure, wherevnto no foreſight is able to reſiſt, but that it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient for them to folow him, by whome it is (as I haue ſaid) gouerned. And who doubteth that <hi>Biblis</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Biblys.</note> knew it not to be euil to loue hir brother? Who wil gaine ſay that it was not manifeſt to <hi>Leander,</hi> that<note place="margin">Leander.</note> he mighte drowne in <hi>Heleſpont,</hi> in his fortunate time, if he caſt him ſelfe therein? And none wyll deny that <hi>Paſiphe</hi> knew not a man to be more faire tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<note place="margin">Paſiphe.</note> Bul? and yet they &amp; ech one ouercome with an amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous pleaſure, r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ting all knowledge, folowed the ſame. Then if it haue power to take knowledge from ſhe learned, takyng away the witt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the wyſe, they ſhall haue nothing leſt: but if from the ſtrong and curteous, it ſhall take away the little witte they haue, it ſhall yet increaſe them in their vertues, and ſo they ſhall become more than the wiſe enamoured. Further, Loue hath this propretie, it is a thing that can not long be hidde: and in reueling himſelf, he is wont oftentimes to bring greuous perils, wherunto what remedy ſhall the wiſe giue that hath nowe loſt his witte? He ſhall giue none at all, but the ſtrong that vſeth his force can helpe in a perill both himſelfe and others. The curteous thorowe his curteſie ſhall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10967:16"/>
with grateful beneuolence winne the myndes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, whereby he may be both holpen and conſidered, and others alſo for his ſake. Sée now what it is to be of your iudgement. She was by the Quéene anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<note place="margin">The quenes laſt ſentence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the thirde question.</note> vnto, thus: If ther were ſuch a one as you ſpeake of, who ſhoulde then be wiſe? not one. But if hée, whome you propounde wiſe, and enamoured of you, ſhuld be made a foole, he is not to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Gods forbid, that that wherof you ſpeake, ſhoulde come to paſſe. And yet wée will not denie but that the wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e know the euill, and do it: but for al that we wil ſay, that they thereby loſe not their witte, foraſmuch as what time it pleaſeth them with the reaſon thei haue to bridle their willes, they will reduce them ſelues to their accuſtomed witte, guiding their motions in a due and ſtraight ordre. And in this maner their loue ſhal be altogether, or at the leaſt, a long time kepte ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, and that without any doubtfull diligence, the which ſhall not happen to one of little witte, be he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo ſtrong or curteous. And yet if perhappes it do happe, that ſuch loue be diſcouered, a wiſe man will with a hundred foreſightes, ſhut vp the eyes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the tattlers therof, and ſhal prouide a ſafetie both for his owne honour, as for the honour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f his loued Lady<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And if néede of ſafetie be, the helpe of the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e can not faile. That of the ſtrong becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth leſſe. And the friendes that are gotten by Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, are accuſtomed in aduerſitie to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. What is ſhe of ſo lyttle diſcretion, that is brought to ſuch a iumpe as hath néede of manifeſte helpe? o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that if hir loue be diſcloſed, ſéeketh fame in hauyng loued a Strong or Liberall man? I beléeue
<pb facs="tcp:10967:17"/>
there is none Rich. Let the wiſe then be ſooneſt loued, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oping that he muſt be in eche cauſe more profitable than any of the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The fourth Queſtion, propoſed by MENEDON.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>he Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by hir countenaunce ſeemed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, when <hi>Menedon,</hi> ſyttyng next vnto hir, ſayde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Moſt high and noble Quéene, nowe is it come to my tourne to propound my queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here in your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">First Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedon telleth a tale.</note> Wherfore by your licence, if in my talke I ſhal wade ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long, yet during the ſame, I ſhal firſt of all of you, and next of the ſtanders about, pray pardon: Bicauſe ye can not be made fully to vnderſtand that, which I intende is propounde, vnleſſe a tale, that peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall not be ſhort, doe precede the ſame: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe wordes thus ſhe began to ſay: In the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey where I was borne, I remember there was a noble knight, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting riche, the whiche loued in moſt loyall louè, a noble Gentlewoman, borne like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there, whome hée tooke to wiſe: Of whome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10967:17"/>
as ſhe was, exceding faire: an other knight cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<note place="margin">Tarolfo a Knight was enamored of a Ladie.</note> 
                  <hi>Tarolfo</hi> was after enamored, and with ſo great good will loued hir, as he ſawe nothing he more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red than hir: And in ſundry ſortes, now with paſſing by before hir houſe, now iuſting, now at the barri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, now with the often ſending hir meſſangers, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture promiſing hir greate giftes, whereby ſhe might know his intent, and now with other like fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes he indeuoured him ſelfe to purchaſe hir loue. All which things the Lady cloſely ſupported, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſigne or good aunſwere to the knight, ſaying to hir ſelf: When as this knight ſhall eſpie, that he can haue neither anſwere ne yet good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of me, perhappes he wil forbeare any further, either to loue me, or to giue me theſe allurementes. Nowe for all this, <hi>Tarolfo</hi> ſurceſſed not, following the precepts of <hi>Ouid,</hi> who ſayth, that a man muſt not thorowe the hardneſſe of a woman leaue to perſeuer, bicauſe with continuance the ſoft water pierceth the harde ſtone. The Lady doubting leaſt theſe things ſhoulde come to the eares of hir huſbande, and that he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that the ſame happened thorowe hir good will, purpoſed to let him vnderſtand the ſame. But yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being perſuaded thorow better aduiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhe ſaid, I might (if I tell him) moue ſuch a broile betwirte<note place="margin">The gift re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by the Lady of Tarolfo, to withdrawe him from lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> them, as I ſhould neuer after liue a merry life, and therfore he would be ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of by ſome other means, and ſo ſhe imagined a tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e guile. She ſent to <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolfo,</hi> ſaying, that if he loued hir ſo wel as he made ſhewe of, ſhe would require one thing at his hands, the which if ſhe receiued, ſhe ſware by hir Gods, and by that loyaltie that ought to be in a Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:10967:18"/>
that ſhe woulde accompliſhe all his deſire. And if he would not giue hir that ſhe required, he ſhould then content him ſelfe no further to allure hir hereafter, but in what he would be willing ſhe ſhuld reueale to hir huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. The gift ſhe required was this. She ſaid ſhe woulde haue in that countrey in the moneth of <hi>Ianuarie,</hi> a verie faire Garden, and large, repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed wyth hearbes, floures, and bloſſomed trées and fruites, as if it were in the moneth of <hi>May:</hi> ſaying to hir ſelfe: This is an impoſſible thing, ſo that in<note place="margin">Tarolfo to performe his ꝓmis ſought ſtrange cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes.</note> this ſort I ſhall ridde him from me. <hi>Tarolfo</hi> hearing this demaunde, &amp; although it ſéemed vnto him impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be done, and that he knew very wel to what ende ſhe required the ſame, anſwered, that he would neuer reſt, neyther yet returne into hir preſence, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuch time he might giue hir the demaunded gift: And ſo forthwith departed his countrey with ſuch a conueniente companie as pleaſed hym to take wyth him. He ſought al the weſt partes for counſell howe to attaine to his deſire, but not finding there that hée looked for, ſought the moſt hote regions, and ſo came into <hi>Theſſalia,</hi> as he had bene ſent by a diſcrete man for that purpoſe. And hauing made his aboue there many dayes, not yet finding that he ſought for: it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, that being now almoſt deſperate of his deſire,<note place="margin">Tarolfo found an old man called Thebane.</note> and riſing one morning before the ſunne prepared to enter the dawning day, he al alone began to wander y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> miſerable plaines, that were now: al imbrued with Romaine bloud: and hauing trauailed a long while vpon the ſame, he ſodainly eſpied before him at the foote of a mountaine, a man not yong, nor of to many yores, bearded, ſmall &amp; very ſpare of perſon, whoſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10967:18"/>
ſhewed him to be but poore, who romed hither &amp; thither gathering herbs, &amp; with a little knife digged vp ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry rootes, wherof he had filled one of the ſkirts of his cote: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <hi>Tarolfo</hi> ſaw, he meruelled not a little, and doubted greatly leaſt it had ben ſome other thing, but after that his ayme did certenly aſſure him to be a man, he drew nere vnto him, ſaluted him, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aſked him who he was, of whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; what he made there at ſo timely an houre. To whome the old man anſwered: I am of <hi>Thebes, &amp; Thebane</hi> is my name, and I go vp &amp; downe this plaine, gathering of theſe herbes, to the ende y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> with the iuyce thereof, I make diuers neceſſarie and profitable things for diuers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mities, wherby I may haue wher withall to liue: And to come at this houre, it is néede and not delight that conſtraineth me. But who are you, that in cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance reſembleth noble, and walk here al alone ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie. To whom <hi>Tarolfo</hi> anſwered: I am of the extremes of the weſt, very riche, and vanquiſhed of my conceipts, pricked forwards to an enterpriſe, not being able hytherto to atchieue the ſame, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be the better able without impediment to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row my happe, I goe thus all alone wandring. To whome <hi>Thebane</hi> ſayde: Do you not know the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the place, and what it is? Wherfore haue you rather taken your way on the other ſide? You might eaſily here be rebuked with furious ſpirites. <hi>Tarol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo</hi> anſwered: God can doe here, as elſe where, it is he that hath my life and honour in his handes: lette him doe with me according to his pleaſure: for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly death ſhoulde be to me a riche treaſure. Then ſayde <hi>Thebane:</hi> What is that your enterpriſe, for
<pb facs="tcp:10967:19"/>
the which not beyng able to perfourme it) you abide thus ſorowfull? To whom <hi>Tarolfo</hi> aunſwered: It is ſuch as ſéemes vnto me impoſſible to be able euer to attaine, ſince hitherto I haue here found no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. Then ſaid <hi>Thebane:</hi> Dare ye vtter it? <hi>Tarol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo</hi> aunſwered: Yea. But what profiteth it? Perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture nothing ſayde <hi>Thebane,</hi> but what doth it hurt? Then ſayde <hi>Tarolfo.</hi> I ſéeke counſell howe<note place="margin">Tarolpho re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeth to Thebane his promis made to his Lady of a garden ful of floures in the month of Ianuarie.</note> may be had in the coldeſt moneth, a garden full of floures, fruites, and hearbes, as farre as if it were in the moneth of May, neither do I finde who can ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in either helpe me, or giue me encouragement that it is poſſible to be had. <hi>Thebane</hi> ſtayde a while in a muſe without aunſwere, and after ſayde: You and many others do iudge the ſkill and vertue of men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their garments. If my goods were ſuch as are yours, you woulde not haue lingred ſo long in diſcouoring your lacke: or if peraduenture you had founde me néere to ſome rich Prince as you haue in gathering of hearbes. But many times vnder the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt veſture are hidden<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the greateſt treaſures of ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: and therefore no one concealeth his lacke, to whome is proffered counſel or helpe: And if therfore he open the ſame, it can not preiudice him at al. But what would ye giue to him that ſhould bring to effect that which you goe about thus ſéeking for? <hi>Taralfo</hi> beheld him in the face, as he vttred theſe words, and doubted leſt he went about to deride him, for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to him incredible, that he ſhuld be able to bring y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame to paſſe vnleſſe he were a God: notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding he anſwered hym thus: I haue vnder my rule in my countrey many ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tles, and there withall great trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10967:19"/>
all the which I would participate in the midſt<note place="margin">Theban pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolpho to make him the garden.</note> with him that wold do me ſo great a pleaſure. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid <hi>Thebane,</hi> if ye would do ſo muche for me, I ſhould no more néede to go thus about, in gathering of herbes. Aſſuredly ſaid <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> if thou be able to giue true effect to that thou promiſeſt, and giueſt me it in déede, thou ſhalte neuer néede to carke ne yet to trouble thy ſelfe to become riche: but how and when canſt thou bring me this to paſſe? Then ſayde <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane,</hi> the tyme when, ſhal be at your choiſe, but for the maner howe, trouble not your ſelfe. And I will go with you, truſting to the wordes and promiſes ye haue made me, and when we ſhal be there, where it pleaſeth you to be, commande what you would haue done, and I ſhall without faile performe the ſanie.</p>
               <p>Of this fortunate happe <hi>Tarolfo</hi> was ſo wel conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in him ſelfe, as litle more gladneſſe could he haue receyued, if he had then helde his Lady embraced in hys armes, and ſayde: Friende, to me it ſéemeth long, vntill thou haue performed, that thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, wherefore let vs depart without further tari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and go thither where this is to be done. <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane</hi> caſt away his herbes, and tooke his bookes and other thinges neceſſary to his ſcience, and with <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolfo</hi> tooke his iourney: and in ſhort time they both came vnto the deſired Citie, very néere vnto the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the which the Garden had bene required to be made. Where as all ſecrete and cloſe they repoſed them ſelues vntil the wiſhed time. And now the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth being entred, <hi>Tarolfo</hi> commaunded the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to be made, to the ende he might giue the ſame to his loued lady. So ſoone as <hi>Thebane</hi> had receiued
<pb facs="tcp:10967:20"/>
this commaundemente, he taried the night enſuyng, the which being once come, he ſaw the hornes of the Moone gathered into a perfect roundneſſe, &amp; to ſhine vpon the frequented earth. Then he went him all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone forth of the citie, leauing his apparel apart, bare legged, and his diſſheueled lockes hanging vpon his naked ſhoulders. The reſtleſſe degrées of the night did paſſe: birdes, wilde beaſtes, and men, wythout any noiſe did take their reſt: the vnfallen leaues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mouing did hang vpon the trées, and the moiſt aire abode in mylde peace: Onely the ſtarres dyd ſhine, when as he oftentimes went about the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, &amp; came to a place on a riuers ſide, which it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to choſe for his Garden. There he ſtretched forth his arme thrée times towardes the ſtarres, and turning him ſelfe vnto them, he as often bathed his white locks in the running ſtreame, crauing as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times with a moſt high voice their helpe: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſetting his knées to the hard earth, began thus to ſaye: Oh night, moſt, faithfull ſecreſer of high<note place="margin">The inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call of The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane.</note> things, and you, oh ye ſtarres, the which together with the Moone, do ſuccede the ſplendant day: &amp; thou oh ſingular <hi>Hecates,</hi> become an helper to this my begon enterpriſe, and thou oh holie <hi>Ceres,</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuer of the ample face of the earth: And you what ſoeuer verſes, either artes, or herbes, and thou what ſoeuer earth bringing forth vertuous plants, &amp; thou oh aire, windes, mountaines, riuers and lakes, and eche God of the woddes, and of the ſecrete night, by whoſe helpe I haue heretofore made the runnyng ſtreames to recule, inforcing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to returne to their ſprings, and things running, to become firme, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10967:20"/>
things firme to become running, and that haſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo giuen power to my verſes to drye vp the Seas, that I at my pleaſure might ſearch the bottom ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, &amp; to make the cloudie times cleare, &amp; (at my wil) to fill the cleare heauens with obſcure cloudes, to make the windes to ceaſſe, and to turne as it ſéemed me beſt: breaking therwith the harde iawes of the fearefull dragons, making alſo the ſtanding woddes to moue, and the hault mountaines to tremble, and to returne to their dead bodies out of the Lake <hi>Stix</hi> thoſe their ſhadowes, and aliue to come forth of their ſepultures: and ſometimes thée O<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Moone to drawe to thy perfect roundneſſe: the attaining wherevnto a ring of Baſons was wont to be an helpe, makyng alſo the cleare face of the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne many times to become pale, be ye all preſent, and aide me with your helpe. I haue at this inſtant néede of the ſappe and iuyce of hearbes, thorowe the which I may make in part, the dry earth faſtned thorowe <hi>Autumne,</hi> and after thorowe the withering colde Winter, ſpoiled of his floures, fruites, and hearbes, to become flouring, and to ſpring before the due terme. And hauing thus ſaid he ſayde after, many other thinges ſoftely, which hée added to his prayers. And thoſe being ended, and he a while ſilent, the ſtarres gaue not their light in vain. For more ſwifter than y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> flight of the wighteſt bird,<note place="margin">Theban was caried in the aire in a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot led by. ij Dragons.</note> there appeared before him a Chariot drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by two dragons, whervpon he mounted, &amp; taking the raines of the bridles of the two bridled dragons in his hand, was caried into the aire. He then leauing <hi>Spayne,</hi> &amp; all <hi>Affrica,</hi> toke his iorney by other Regions, &amp; firſt ſought for the Ile of <hi>Crete,</hi> &amp; from thence after with
<pb facs="tcp:10967:21"/>
a ſhort courſe he ſought <hi>Pelion, Othrys,</hi> and <hi>Oſſa,</hi> the mount <hi>Neriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Pachynꝰ, Pelorus</hi> &amp; <hi>Appaennine.</hi> Vpon them all plucking vp, &amp; with a ſharp ſickle cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe ſuch rootes and herbes as beſt liked him, neyther forgat he thoſe whych he had before gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red when as he was found by <hi>Tarolfo</hi> in <hi>Theſſalia.</hi> Hée tooke ſtones alſo vppon the mounte <hi>Cauſacus,</hi> and of the ſandes of <hi>Ganges:</hi> and out of <hi>Libia,</hi> he brought tongs of venemous ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. He ſerched the watrie bankes of <hi>Rodanus,</hi> of <hi>Senna</hi> at <hi>Parys,</hi> of the great <hi>Po,</hi> of <hi>Arnus,</hi> of the imperiall <hi>Tyber,</hi> of <hi>Nifeus,</hi> of <hi>Tana,</hi> and of <hi>Danuby:</hi> vppon thoſe eke gathering ſuch herbes as ſéemed to him moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for his purpoſe, putting theſe together with the others, gathered on the toppes of the ſauage moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. He alſo ſought the Ilandes of <hi>Leſbos</hi> and <hi>Pathmos,</hi> and euery other, wherin he perceiued any profitable thing to be had for his attempt: With all the which things he came (the thirde day beyng not yet paſt) to that place from whence he departed, and the drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that only had felt the odour of the gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red herbes, did caſt of their olde hides of many yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and were with new renued and become yong.<note place="margin">The ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies vſed in making the garden. Ceres.</note> There he diſmounted from his chariot, and of the gréene earth he made two altares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> on his right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that of <hi>Hecates:</hi> and on the left that of the renuing goddeſſe: that being done, and deuout fires kindled thervpon, with lockes diſperpled vpon the old ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, he began with a murmuring noiſe to go about the ſame, &amp; with gathered bloud oftentimes he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprent the blaſing brandes. After he placed the ſame bloud vpon the altars, ſomtimes ſoftning therwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10967:21"/>
the grounde, appoynted for hys Garden: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, he ſoftned agayne the ſelfe ſame thrée times, with fire, water, and Sulpher, ſetting after a great veſſell full of bloud, milke, and water, vpon the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning brandes, which he cauſed to boile a good ſpace, and put thereto the herbes and rootes, gathered in ſtraunge places, minglyng therwith alſo diuers ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and floures of vnknowen hearbes, he added ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto ſtones, ſoughte in the extreame partes of the eaſt, and deawe gathered the nightes paſte, together with the fleſh of infamous Witches, the ſtones of a Wolfe, the hinder part of a fat <hi>Cinyphis,</hi> &amp; the ſkin of a <hi>Chilinder.</hi> And laſtly a Lyuer, with the whole lunges of an exceding olde Harte: and herewithal a thouſande other things, both without name, and ſo ſtraunge, as my memorie can not againe tell them. After he toke a drie bough of an Oliue trée, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with began to mingle all theſe thinges together. In doing whereof, the dry bough began to waxe gréene, and within a while after to beare leaues, &amp; not long after the new apparelling therof, it was laden with blacke Oliues. As <hi>Thebane</hi> ſawe this, he tooke the boyling licours, and began therewithal to ſprinkle &amp; water in euery place the choſen ſoyle, wherin he had ſette ſlippes of ſo many woddes, as he woulde haue trées, and of as many ſortes as could be founde. The which licour the earth had no ſooner taſted, but that it began to ſpring: yelding floures and new herbes, and the dry ſettes began to become all gréene &amp; fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full plants. All this being done, <hi>Theban</hi> entring the Citie, returned to <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> whome he found all in a muſe, fearing to be ſcorned thorowe hys long abode,
<pb facs="tcp:10967:22"/>
to whom he ſaid. <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> the thing (thou requiredſt)<note place="margin">Tarolfo offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſhe demaunded.</note> is done to thy liking. Theſe newes pleaſed <hi>Tarolfo</hi> not a little, and happening the day folowing to be a great ſolemnitie in the Citie, he wente into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his loued Lady, that had not now ſéene him of a long time paſt: and thus he ſayde vnto hir: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame, after a long and tedious trauaile, I haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that which you haue commaunded, and when as it ſhal pleaſe you to ſée it, or to take it, it is redy at your pleaſure. She in ſéeing him, maruelled much, and the more, hearing what he ſaid, &amp; not beleuing the ſame to be true, made him this anſwere: It plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me right well, ye ſhall let me ſée it to morrowe. The ſecond day was come, and <hi>Tarolfo</hi> went again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to his lady, and ſayde: Madame, maye it pleaſe you to walke to the Garden, the which you required to haue this colde moneth. She then being accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied<note place="margin">The Lady goeth to ſee the garden.</note> with many others, was moued to ſée the ſame. And they al being come to the garden, entred therin by a faire portall: wheras they felt not the like cold as abrode, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame to haue a ſwéete te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perats aire. The lady we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t about y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame, &amp; into euery corner ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, gathering both hearbes and floures, whereof ſhée ſawe it very plentifull. And thus muche more alſo had the vertue of the ſperſed licours wroughte, that the fruites which <hi>August</hi> was accuſtomed to bring forth, the trées there in this ſauage tyme, did yelde them very faire, wherof ſundry did eate, that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied the lady thither. This Garden ſéemed to the Lady exceding faire and admirable, neither did ſhe thinke to haue euer ſéene the like: and ſince ſhe ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ways knew it to be a true Garden, &amp; the knight
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:10967:22"/>
to haue perfourmed hir requeſt, ſhe turned towards<note place="margin">The Lady graunteth the amorous demaund of Tarolfo.</note> him, and ſayde: Without doubt ſir Knight, ye haue deſerued my loue, and I am ready to ſtand to my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. But I woulde pray you of this fauour, that it would pleaſe you to tary the tune or euer ye require me to your deſire, that my Knight be gone a hunting or into ſome other place out of the Citie, to the ende ye may the more ſafely, and without any ſuſpition, take your delight. This contented <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> who left hir the Garden, and ſo departed. This Garden was manifeſt to the whole countrey, although neuer a one knew of a long time, how it came to paſſe. And the Lady that had now receiued it, al ſorowful depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the ſame, returning to hir chamber, full of noyſome care and griefe, bethinking hir in what ſort ſhe might returne backe according to hir promiſe: &amp; as not finding any léeful excuſe, ſo much the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed hir care. The which thing hir huſband eſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he began many times &amp; often to maruell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, &amp; to aſke the cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hir grief, to whome ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhe ailed nothing, being baſhful to diſcouer to him hir giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> promiſſe for hir craued gifte, doubting leſt in ſo doing, he ſhuld accompt hir for leude. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhe being vnable to withſtand the continual inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of hir huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> now ſtil importunatly deſired to know y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cauſe of hir annoy, diſcourſed the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning to the ende, &amp; that therfore ſhe abode thus penſiue. The huſband hearing this, of long time ſuſpected no leſſe, &amp; therby knowing in his conceipt, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> puritie of the lady, thus ſaid vnto hir: Goe &amp; couertly kéepe thine othe, &amp; liberally performe to <hi>Tarolfo</hi> what thou haſt promiſed. For he hath
<pb facs="tcp:10967:23"/>
with his great toile of right deſerued the ſame. And hauing thus ſayde, the lady began to wéepe, and to ſay vnto him: The Gods ſeuer me farre from ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ault. In no wiſe will I ſo doe: I will rather ridde my ſelfe of life than do any thing diſpleaſant to you, or diſhonour to your perſon. To whome the knight replied, ſaying: Wife, for this matter I will that ye do no iniurie to your ſelfe, neither yet conceiue any griefe therfore, for in no wiſe ſhall it diſpleaſe me, go therfore, and performe what ye haue promiſed: for ye ſhall be neuer a whit the leſſe deare to me: But as ye haue performed this your promiſe, ſo take ye bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hede hereafter of ſuch like, although y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> demanded gift may ſeme vnto you impoſſible to be had. As the lady perceiued the will of hir huſbande, ſhe decked &amp; trimmed hir &amp; made hir ſelf very faire, toke company<note place="margin">The Lady preſenteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir ſelfe to Tarolfo.</note> with hir, and ſo went to <hi>Tarolfos</hi> lodging, and all bepainted with baſhefulneſſe preſented hir ſelfe vnto him. <hi>Tarolfo</hi> as ſoone as he ſaw hir, all merua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ling, roſe from <hi>Thebane,</hi> and encountred hir with great gladneſſe, and very honourably receiued hir, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng the cauſe of hir comming. To whome ſhe aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, I am come to be wholly at your will, do with me as it pleaſeth you. Then ſayde <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> ye make me to muſe aboue meaſure, conſidering the time and the company wherwith ye are come: This can not be without ſome great alteration betwéene you and your huſbande, tell me therfore I pray you, how the matter goth. The lady then ſhewed <hi>Tarolfo</hi> fully in order the whole matter and how it went: the which <hi>Tarolfo</hi> hearing, he began then to enter into a farre greater admiration than he had euer done before, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10967:23"/>
greatly to bethinke him hereof, and ſo in the ende to<note place="margin">The libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolfo towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing hir of hir promis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> conceiue the great liberalitie of the huſband, that had ſent his wife vnto him; wherupon he ſaid to himſelf: Whatſoeuer he be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſhould ſo much as but thinke villanie towardes ſuch a knight, were ſurely worthy of great blame: and ſo taking and talking with the Lady, he thus ſayde vnto hir: Madame, like a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Lady, ye haue performed that to me due is: for the which cauſe I accompt that receiued of your han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that I haue of you deſired, and therfore when it ſhall pleaſe you, ye may returne to your huſbande, and thanke him (I pray you) on my behalfe, for this his ſo great a pleaſure done vnto me, and excuſe me of the ſolie I haue heretofore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted towards him, aſſuring him, that hereafter I ſhal neuer put the like in practiſe. The lady giuing great thanks to <hi>Tarol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo</hi> for that his ſo great curteſie, merily departed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and returned to hir huſbande, to whom ſhe recited in ordre all that had ben happened. But <hi>Theban,</hi> nowe comming to <hi>Tarolfo</hi> demaunded how the caſe ſtode. <hi>Tarolfo</hi> declared vnto him the whole diſcourſe. To whom <hi>Theban</hi> then ſayd: and I, ſhal I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loſe that which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt promiſed me? <hi>Tarolfo</hi> anſwered: no, but when it pleaſeth thée, take thou halfe of al the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels &amp; treaſures I haue in ſort heretofore promiſed thée. For I acknowledge, that thou haſt fully ſerued my turne. To whome <hi>Theban</hi> aunſwered: It may<note place="margin">Liberalitie of Thebane towardes Tarolfo.</note> neuer pleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gods, ſince the knight was ſo liberal to thée of his wife, &amp; thou againe waſt not a villaine to him in that his offer, that I become leſſe than cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. For aboue all things in the worlde it conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me, in that I haue ſerued thy turne: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:10967:24"/>
I will, that all that I ought to receyue in guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of my trauaile remaine all thine, in ſuch ſort as it hath euer bene heretofore: neither would he take of that was <hi>Tarolfos</hi> any thing at all. It is now doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the propoſer.</note> in whether of theſe was the greateſt liberalitie, either in the knight y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> had giuen libertie to his wife to go to <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> either in <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> who ſent the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (whom he had always deſired, and for whoſe ſake he had done ſo much, to come to that iumpe, whervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men, when as ſhe came vnto him) backe to hir huſband frée: or in <hi>Thebane,</hi> who hauing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned his countrey (being now olde) for to gaine the promiſed rewardes, and being come thether, toi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him ſelfe to bring that to an ende, which he had promiſed, wherby he iuſtly deſerued y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame, did now remit the whole to <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> and remained poore as he was of the firſt. Very excellent is both the tale &amp;<note place="margin">The iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Queene vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fourth question.</note> the demaunde, ſayd the Quéene. Of trouth eache one was very liberall, conſidering the firſt of his honour, the ſecond of his laſciuious deſire, and the third that of his rewarded riches; was very curteous. Nowe if we will knowe which of them vſed the greateſt libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie or curteſie: It is méete we conſider whether of the thrée déedes is moſte acceptable, the which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well wayed, we ſhall manifeſtly knowe the moſt liberall, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auſe who moſt giueth, is to be helde moſt liberall: of the which thrée, the one is deare, that is Honour, the which <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi> vanquiſhyng <hi>Perſes,</hi> king of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> rather deſired than the gained treaſures. The ſecond is to be fled, that is, the wanton delights of <hi>Venus,</hi> according to the ſentence of <hi>Sophocles,</hi> and of <hi>Xenocrates,</hi> ſaying: That luſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10967:24"/>
is to be fled as a furious gouernement. The third is not to be deſired, that is Riches: forſomuch as the moſt times they are noiſome to a vertuous life, and to ſuch a one as can vertuouſly liue with moderate<note place="margin">Diuers Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſt pore, and yet vertuous.</note> pouertie, as liued <hi>Marcus Curtius, Attilius Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> and <hi>Valerius Publicola,</hi> as by their workes is manifeſt. If then of theſe thrée, only Honour is to be helde deare, and the others not, he vſed the greateſt liberalitie that gaue his wife to another, although he did leſſe than wiſely therin. He was alſo the chiefeſt in liberalitie, wherin the others folowed him: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to our iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he that gaue his wife in whome conſiſted his honour, was aboue the reſt, the moſt liberall. I (ſayde <hi>Menedon</hi>) agrée, that in<note place="margin">The reply of Men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as much as ye haue thus ſayde, it be as you ſay: but yet eche one of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other ſéemeth to me, to be more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall, and ye ſhall heare howe. It is very true, that the firſt graunted his wife, but he vſed therin not ſo gret a liberalitie as ye ſpeake of, bicauſe if he would haue denied hir, he might not iuſtly haue done it, by reaſon of the othe ſhe made, the which was conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for hir to kéepe: and therfore who giueth that he may not denie, doth but well in making himſelfe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and it was but a trifle he gaue: and therfore (as I haue ſayde) eche one of the other was more curteous. And for that (as it is already ſayde) <hi>Tarolfo</hi> had now a long time deſired this lady, and loued hir farre aboue all others, he for to attaine hir, had of long time abode great troubles, offering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for to ſatiſfie hir requeſt, to ſéeke forth things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible to be had, the which nowe obtained, he deſerued (through hir promiſed faith) to obtain hir
<pb facs="tcp:10967:25"/>
alſo, whome (as we ſay) being obteined, there is no doubt but that the honor of the the huſband, and the releaſe of that ſhe had promiſed (the which he relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) was in his hande. Then was he, to conclude, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall both of the honor of the huſbande, of the othe of his lady, and of his owne long deſire. It is a greate matter to haue endured long thirſt, and to come to a pleaſant fountaine, and not to drinke, but to ſuffer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to drinke. The thirde was alſo very liberall, conſidering that pouertie is one of the moſt lothſome things of the worlde to beare, for ſo much as it is the chaſer away both of mirth and reſt, a flier of honors, a frequenter of vertue, and the inducer of crabbed<note place="margin">Euery one f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ieth pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> care, ſo that euery one naturally endeuoure them ſelues wyth a fiery deſire to flie the ſame, the which deſire is ſo kyndled in many, to the ende to lyue very ſplendantly in reſte, as they giue them ſelues no leſſe to diſhoneſt gaine, than to diſordinate ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, peraduenture not knowing, or not otherwayes being able to féede that their deſire: which is cauſe many times either of death or exile. How much then ought the riches to pleaſe &amp; to be acceptable to them that in due ſorte doe both gaine and poſſeſſe them? And who wil doubt that <hi>Theban</hi> was not moſt poore if he beholde howe he abandoning his nightes reſt, wente gathering of hearbes, and digging vp of roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, in doubtfull places for the better ſuſtentation of hys poore life. And that this pouertie did occupie hys vertue, may be alſo beleued, in hearing how <hi>Tarolfo</hi> did déeme to be by him diſceiued, when he beheld him apparelled in vile veſture, and ſeing him deſirous to ſhake of that miſerie to become riche, knowing howe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10967:25"/>
he came as farre as from <hi>Theſſalia,</hi> into <hi>Spayne,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarding him ſelf to perillous chaunces thorow doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iourneys and vncertaine aire, to the ende to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme the promiſſe he had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> made, and to receyue the like from an other. Alſo it may be euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſéene, that without doubt who giues him ſelf to ſuch and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſeries to the ende to flie pouertie, knoweth the ſame to be full of all grief &amp; troubles. And how much the more he hath ſhaken of the greateſt pouertie, and is entred a rich life, ſo much the more is the ſame life acceptable vnto hym. Then who that is become of poore, riche, if therwith his life doth delight him, how great, and what maner of liberalitie doth he vſe, if he giue the ſame away, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenteth to returne to that ſtate, the which he hath with ſo many troubles fled? Aſſuredly he doth a thing exceding great and liberal. And this ſéemeth farre greater than the reſt, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring<note place="margin">Olde folkes commonly couetous.</note> alſo of the age of the giuer, that was now olde: foraſmuch as Auarice was wont to be continually of greater force in olde men than in yong, whervpon I gather, that eche one of the two folowing, hath vſed a greater liberalitie than hath the firſt, ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by you, and the third farre more than either of the others. In howe much your reaſon might bée well by any one defended, ſo well is the ſame defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by you (ſayd the Quéene) but we minde to ſhew vnto you briefly how our iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t rather tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yours ought to take place. Ye will ſay, that he ſhewed no<note place="margin">The quenes ſolution to the fourth queſtion.</note> Liberalitie at all, graunting the vſe of his wife to an other, bicauſe of reaſon it was conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thorow the othe made by the Lady, that he ſhould ſo do, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which ought to be in déede if the othe might holde. But the
<pb facs="tcp:10967:26"/>
wife forſomuch as ſhe is a membre of hir huſband, or rather one body with him, could not iuſtly make ſuch an othe without the will of hir huſbande: and yet if ſhe did make ſuch an othe, it was nothing, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> firſt othe lawfully made, could not with reaſon be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate by any following, chiefly not by thoſe that are not duly made for a neceſſary cauſe. And the maner is in matrimoniall vnitings the man to ſweare to be contente with the woman, and the woman with the man, and neuer to chaunge the one the other for an other. Now then, the woman can not ſweare, and if ſhe do ſweare (as we haue ſayde) ſhe ſweareth for a thing vnlawful, and ſo contrary to the former othe it ought not to preuaile, and not preuailing otherwiſe than for his pleaſure, he ought not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit his wife to <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> and if he doe commit hir to hym, then is he Liberall of his honour, and not <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> as you holde opinion. Neither coulde he bée liberall of his othe in releaſing it, for as much as the othe was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Then onely remained <hi>Tarolfo</hi> liberall of his wanton deſire: the which thing of propre duetie is conuenient for euery man to doe, bicauſe we all tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe reaſon are bounde to baniſh vice, and to folow vertue. And who that doth that, wherevnto he is of reaſon bounde is (as ye haue ſayd) nothing at all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral,<note place="margin">Flie vice and followe vertue.</note> but that which is done more than dutie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, may well and iuſtly be termed Liberalitie. But bicauſe you peraduenture with ſilence argue in your minde, what honour may that be of a chaſte woman to hir huſbande, which ought to be ſo deare: we wil prolong ſomewhat oure talke in ſhewing you, to the ende that ye may the more clearely ſée, that <hi>Tarolfo</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:10967:26"/>
and <hi>Thebane,</hi> of whome we intende next to ſpeake, vſed no liberalitie at all in reſpect of the Knight. Ye ſhal know that chaſtitie together with the other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, yeld none other reward to the poſſeſſours ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,<note place="margin">Chaſtitie a vertue moſt excellent.</note> than honour, the which honour among vertuous men, makes the leaſt vertuous, the moſt excellent. This honour if men with humilitie ſéeke to ſupport it, it maketh them friendes to God, and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to liue, and after death, to poſſeſſe the goodes<note place="margin">The ioy of a man is to haue a good wife.</note> eternal: the which if the woman conſerueth for hir huſbande, he may liue merily, and certaine of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, and frequent in open ſight among the people content to ſée hir for ſuch hir vertues honored amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the moſt high and chiefeſt dames, and in his minde it is a manifeſt token that ſhe is good, feareth God, and loueth him, which is no ſmall pleaſure, ſeing ſhée is giuen him for an euerlaſting companion indiuiſible, ſauing by death: He thorow this obtained fauour is ſéene continually to increaſe, both in ſpirituall and<note place="margin">The grief of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing an euil life.</note> wordly wealth. And ſo on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, he whoſe wife hath defaulte of ſuche vertues, can neuer paſſe one houre with true co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation, nothing is acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and continually the one deſireth the death of the other, he perceiueth him ſelfe thorowe this diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred vice to bée caried in the mouthes of the verieſt miſers, neither ſéemeth it vnto him, that ſuch a fault ſhould not be beleued, of whome ſo euer it is hearde: And if ſhe were largely endowed with all other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, yet this vice ſéemeth to haue ſuch a force as to bring hir in contempt, &amp; to vtter ruine. Then is this honour that maketh the woman both chaſt and good to hir huſbande, a moſt great gift, and ſo is to be held
<pb facs="tcp:10967:27"/>
moſt dearely. Bleſſed may he be called to whom tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe grace is graunted ſuch a gifte, although we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue they are but few, towards whome is borne enuy for ſo gret a benefite. But to returne to our purpoſe, it is to be ſéene how much the Knight did giue. It is not fled our memorie when as ye ſayd, that <hi>Theban</hi> was of the reſt moſt liberall, who being with trouble enriched, hath not doubted to returne into the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of poore eſtate, in gyuing away that which he had gotten. It apparantly appeareth, that ye are euill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with pouertie, who if ſhe come vnto vs me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſurmounteth all riches. <hi>Thebane</hi> now peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note place="margin">The care which ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches bring.</note> thorow the attained wealth, felt him ſelf replete of ſundry ſowre cares. He did nowe imagine that it ſéemed <hi>Tarolfo</hi> to haue done very euill, and therfore woulde practiſe by murdring hym, to recouer againe his Caſtels. He abode in feare to be peraduenture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed of his tenantes. He was entred into care tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the gouernement of his landes. He now knew all the prepared guiles to bée done vnto his coparte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. He ſaw him ſelfe greatly enuied for his riches, and doubted leaſt théeues ſhould ſecretely ſpoile hym therof. He was ſtuffed with ſo many ſuch and ſundry thoughtes and cares, as all quietneſſe was fled from him. Thorowe the which occaſions, calling to minde his former life, and that without ſo many cares hée paſſed the ſame merrily, ſayd to him ſelfe: I deſired to grow riche, to the ende to attaine quiet reſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but I ſée it is the increaſer of troubles and cogitations: ſo is it the flier of quietneſſe: And therefore deſirous to be in his former eſtate, he rendred them all to him by wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me they were gyuen. Pouertie is the refuſed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10967:27"/>
rich, sa goodneſſe vnknowen, a flier of prouocations,<note place="margin">Pouertie highly eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſt.</note> the whiche was of <hi>Diogenes</hi> fully vnderſtoode. As much ſuffiſeth pouertie, as Nature requireth. He li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſafe from euery diſceite that pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly approcheth therewith, neither is he diſabled to attaine to greate honours, that (as wée haue ſayde) vertuouſly liueth therewith: and therefore as <hi>Thebane</hi> reiected this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurement he was not liberall, but wiſe. So gracious he was to <hi>Tarolfo,</hi> in that it pleaſed him to giue the ſame rather to hym than to an other, where as hée might haue beſtowed the ſame vppon many others. Then to conclude, the Knight was more liberal that graunted his honour, than any of the others: And thinke this one thing, that the honour he gaue was not to be againe recouered, the which happeneth not in many other things, as of battailes, proweſſe, and others like: For if they are at one tyme loſt, they are recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at an other, and the ſame is poſſible<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therefore this maye ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſe for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vnto youre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10967:28"/>
               <head>¶ The fift Queſtion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by CLONICO.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the Queene became ſilent, &amp; <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedon</hi> ſatiſfyed, a worthy yong gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man called <hi>Clonico,</hi> that fat next to <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedon,</hi> thus began to ſaye: Moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Quéene, this gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomans tale hath bene ſo excellent, and therwithall ſo long, as I in what I may, ſhall briefly ſhewe vnto you this my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onceipt, to the ende the reſt may the better at their more leaſure ſay theirs. Then for as much as I, although very yong, knew the life of the ſubiects of our Lorde Loue, to be replete with many cares and ſundry pyning prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, yet with ſmall delight I haue long tyme as I was able, fled the like, rather eſchewing than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending them which follow him: And although I was ſundry times tempted, yet with a valiant minde (leauing the pitched ſnares) I alwayes reſiſted: But bicauſe I being not ſtrong enough, coulde no wayes reſiſt that force, wherevnto <hi>Phoebus</hi> was vnable to gainſtand, <hi>Cupide</hi> hauing taken heart to bring mée into the number of his thralles, was taken before I knewe howe. For one day being allured abrode tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the freſh renued time,, walking all merry, &amp; for my delight gathering of ſhell fyſh vpon the ſalte Sea
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:10967:28"/>
bankes, it happened as I tourned mine eyes towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des<note place="margin">Foure yong damſels in a Barke vpon the Sea.</note> the glittering waues, I ſoddaynely ſawe a little Barke comming towardes me; wherin, with one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marined, were foure yong Gentlewomen ſo faire, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was a maruellous thing to behold y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> beauty thei ſéemed to haue. They nowe being approched ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what néere vnto me, and I not hauing as yet turned mine eye from them, ſawe in the middeſt of them an excéeding great light, wherin, as my eſtimation gaue me, me thought I ſawe the fygure of an Angell, very yong, and ſo faire, as I neuer behelde thing more fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer: whome as I thus eyed, me thought he ſaid vnto<note place="margin">Clonico at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanited of Loue.</note> me with a voice farre diſcrepant from ours: O yong foole, perſecuter of our power (and being therwith ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued) I am come hither with foure yong damſels, let thy eye make<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> choiſe of hir for thy maiſtreſſe, that beſt liketh thée. I when I heard this voice, abode all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palled, and deuiſed both with eye and heart to auoyde that which heretofore I had many times fled: but all was booteleſſe, for the ſtrength of my legs ſayled me, &amp; byſide, he had bowe &amp; wyngs to ouertake me quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: wherevpon I in gazing among them, eſpied one ſo faire, ſo benigne of cheare, and ſo piteous of ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaunce, as I imagined to make choiſe of hir, as of a ſinguler mayſtreſſe, ſaying to my ſelfe: This damſel preſenteth hirſelfe ſo humble to my eyes, as aſſuredly ſhe will neuer become enimie to my deſires, as many others haue bene to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whome I haue in beholding full of troubles alwayes ſcorned, but ſhe ſhall rather bée a chaſer awaye of my annoyes: and hauing thus thought, I forthwith anſwered: The gracious beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of that yong damſell, that (O my Lord) ſitteth on
<pb facs="tcp:10967:29"/>
your right hand, makes me deſire to be both to you, and hir, a moſt faithfull ſeruant. I am therefore ready to obey your will, do with me as ſhall beſt like you. I had not ended my tale, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I felt my left ſide woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note place="margin">The. ij. ſhaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Loue are different</note> with a ſhining ſhaft ſhot from the bow which he bare, as me thought y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame was of gold. And aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſaw him as he turned towardes hir, to ſtrike hir with an other of leade. And thus I being in this ſort taken, abode in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſnares I had of long time fled. This yong damſel hath and doth ſo much content mine eye as all other pleaſure is very ſcarce in compariſon of this. The which ſhe eſpying, of long time ſhewed hir ſelfe content: but after that ſhe knew me to be ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with this delight, as no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to loue hir was a thing impoſſible, incontinent ſhée diſcouered hir guile to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with an vndeſerued diſdaine, ſhowing hir ſelfe in apparance a moſt cruell enimie, alwayes tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eye the contrary way, as ſhe happened to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and with wordes, on my part vndeſerued, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes diſpraiſing me, by oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſion wherof, I haue in ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ry ſortes endeuoured my ſelfe both with prayers and humilitie to appeaſe hir crueltie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but beyng vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, I oftentimes bewéepe and lament this my hard fortune, neither can I any wayes withdraw me from<note place="margin">Clonico an vnbeloued Louer.</note> louing hir, but rather how much the more I finde hir cruell, ſo much the more me thinketh the flame of hir pleaſure doth ſet my ſorowful heart on fire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As I tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe occaſions, one day being all ſolitarie in a garden, bewailed my happe with infinite ſighes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with many teares, there came vpon me a ſinguler friend of myne, to wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m part of my griefs were diſcouered, who with pitifull wordes began to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10967:29"/>
comfort me y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> beſt he could, but I giuing thervnto no eare at all, anſwered him, that my miſerie exceded all others. Whervnto he made me this anſwer: A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo much y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> more miſerable (ſayde he) as he either ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieth or reputeth himſelf a miſer: but aſſuredly I haue greater cauſe to lament than haſt thou. I then al an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry turned towards him with a diſdainfull loke, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: And how? Who can haue greter cauſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I? Do not I for good ſeruice receiue euil recompence? Is not my faithful loue rewarded with hatred? So that any may be as ſorrowfull as I, but more he can not bée. Truly (ſayd my friend) I haue greater cauſe of grief<note place="margin">A Louer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with ielouſie reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico the good enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement of his Lady.</note> than haſt thou, and heare how. It is not vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thée, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I haue of long time, &amp; yet doe loue a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman as thou knoweſt: neither was there euer any thyng that I thought might pleaſure hir, which I ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e not my ſelfe with all my witte and power to bring to effecte. And truely when ſhe vnderſtode the ſame, of that I deſired, ſhe made me a gracious gift, the which as I had receiued, and receiuing it at what time it pleaſed me, me thought none by a greate way to haue a life comparable to myne in gladneſſe: only one thing pricked me, that I coulde not make hir be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue how perfectly I loued hir. Further than this, ſhe perceiuing me to loue hir (as I ſayd) paſſed lightly for me. But the Gods that will graunt no worldly good turne without ſome bitterneſſe, to the ende that the<note place="margin">A goodly ſentence.</note> heauenly may be the better knowen, &amp; by conſequent the more deſired, to this they gaue me an other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey without compariſon noiſome, that is, that it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned one day, as I abode with hir all alone, in a ſecret place, ſéeing (without being againe ſéene) who paſſed
<pb facs="tcp:10967:30"/>
by, eſpied a propre yong man, and of a pleaſant coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to come along by vs, whom ſhe behelde as I perceiued, with a fixed eie, and being paſt, ſhe fette a pitifull ſigh, the which I eſpying, ſayde: Alas, do you ſo ſoone repent, as that ye now ſigh for the loue of an other? She, whoſe face was thorowe this occaſion painted with a new rudde, ſwearing by the power of the high Gods, began with many excuſes to endeuor hir ſelf to make me beleue the contrary of that which I had conceiued thorowe the ſigh, but all was to no purpoſe, bicauſe ſhe kindled my heart with an anger ſo exceding fierce, as ſhe made me then almoſt ready to chide with hir, but yet I withhelde me therfrom: And certainely it wil neuer out of my minde but that ſhe loueth him or ſome other better than me: and all thoſe perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the which at other times heretofore ſhe vſed for my helpe, that was, that ſhe loued me bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than ſhe did any other, I nowe eſteme them all in contrary, imagining that ſhe hath fainedly ſayde, and done all that ſhe hath heretofore wrought, wherby I endure intollerable griefe, neither doth any comfort at all preuaile therin: but bicauſe ſhame often times doth bridle the wil I haue rather to ſorrowe me than glad me, I doe not continue my bitter griefe, ſo as I make any apparaunce therof: but briefly I am ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer without cares and cogitations, the which bring me far greater annoy than I willingly would. Lerne then to beare the leſſe griefs, ſince thou ſéeſt the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt with a valiant minde borne of me. To whome I anſwered, that as it ſemed to me, his grief although it wer great, was no wayes to be compared to myne. He anſwered me the contrary, and thus we abode in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:10967:30"/>
a long contention, and in the ende parted without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<note place="margin">The quenes iudgement vpon this fift question.</note> diffinition. Wherefore, I pray you that ye wyll ſay your iudgement hereof. Yong Gentleman, ſayd the Quèene, great is that paine of yours, and greate wrong doth the damſell committe in not louing you. But yet at al times your grief may by hope be eaſed, the which happeneth not to your companion, bicauſe that ſince he is once entred in ſuſpect, nothing is able to draw it away. Therfore continually whileſt Loue laſteth he ſorroweth without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort: So that in our iudgement greater ſéemeth the griefe of the iealous, than that of the vnloued Louer. Then ſaid <hi>Clonico,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinion of Clonico.</note> Oh noble Quéene, ſince you ſaye ſo, it playnely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that you haue alwayes bene loued againe, of him whome you haue loued, by occaſion whereof, ye hardely knowe what my payne is. Howe may it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that iealouſie bryngeth greater griefe than is that I féele, forſomuch as the iealous poſſeſſeth that he deſireth, &amp; may in holding the ſame, take more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light therof in one houre, than in a long time after to féele any paine thorowe want thereof: and neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe he may (thorow experience) abandon ſuch ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, if it happen that this iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be found falſe: But I being kindled with a fiery deſire, how much y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> more I ſée my ſelfe farre off from the attaining the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame, ſo much the more I burne and conſume my ſelf aſſaulted of a thouſande inſtigations, neyther is any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>perience able to helpe me therein, bycauſe thorowe the often reprouing hir, and finding hir euery houre more ſharpe, I liue deſperate. Wherefore your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere ſéemeth contrary to the truth, bycauſe I doubt not but that it is much better to hold wyth ſuſpition,
<pb facs="tcp:10967:31"/>
than to deſire with teares. That amorous flame that doth ſhine in our eyes, and that euery houre doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orne our ſight with the greater beautie, doeth neuer conſent (replied the Quéene) that we loue in vaine, as<note place="margin">The Quene replieth.</note> you affirme: but for al that it is not vnknowen to vs, how great and what maner of payne that is, both of the one and the other: and therefore as our anſwere hath bene confirmable to the truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> one thing we wil ſhewe to you. It is manifeſt that thoſe things which moſt do hynder the quiet of the minde, are cares, the whiche are ſome of them come to a merrie ende, ſo ſome we ſée to ende with great ſorrowe, wherof, how much more the minde is repleate, ſo muche the more hath it of griefe, and chieflieſt, when as the ſame are noiſome: and that the iealous haue more ſtore therof than haue you, is manifeſt, bicauſe you héede nothing elſe but only to get the good will of the damſel whome ye loue, the which not being able to attaine, is to you a griefe moſt grieuous: but yet it is certayne that it may eaſly come to paſſe to attaine the ſame at one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, not thinking thereof (forſomuch as womens heartes are inconſtant) byſides peraduenture ſhe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you not withſtanding (to proue if you alſo loue hir) ſhe ſheweth the contrary, and ſo perhappes wyll ſhewe vntill ſuche time as ſhe ſhall be well aſſured of your loue, ſo that with theſe thoughtes, hope can mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate vnfained griefe: but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> iealous hath hys mind full fraught of infinite cares, agaynſt the which ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hope nor other delyght can bring comfort, or eaſe the paine. For he ſtandeth intentiue to giue a Lawe<note place="margin">The effectes of Iealouſie.</note> to the wandring eyes, the which his poſſeſſor can not giue. He will and doth endeuour himſelfe to giue a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10967:31"/>
Law to the féete, to the hands, and to euery other act of his Miſtreſſe. He will be a circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpect knower both of hir thoughts, and of hir myrth, interpreting euery thing in euill parte towardes him ſelfe, beleuing that eache one deſireth and loueth hir whome hée loueth. Likewiſe he imagineth euery word that ſhe ſpeaketh to be twaine, &amp; full of diſceite. And if he euer commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any detractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towards hir, it is death to him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre it, imagining to be by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> like meanes deceiued. He wil with coniectures ſhut vp the ways of the aire, &amp; of the earth. And briefly the heauens, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> earth, birds, beaſtes, &amp; euery other creature that he thinketh doth hinder his deuiſes. And to remoue him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, hope hath no place, bicauſe in this doing, if he find the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man faithfull, he thinketh that ſhe eſpieth that which he doth, and is therfore hedefull therin. If he findeth that he ſéeketh for, and that he would not finde, who is more dolorous than he? If peraduenture ye thinke that the imbracing hir in his armes be ſo great a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light vnto him as ſhould mitigate theſe pangs, your iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is then falſe, bicauſe ſuch maner of colling bringeth him in choller, in thinking y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> others as well as he, hath imbraced hir in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> like ſort: &amp; if the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peraduenture do louingly entertaine him, he demeth that ſhe doeth it to the ende to remoue him from ſuch his imaginations, and not for the true loue ſhe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him. If he finde hir maliciouſly diſpoſed, he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that ſhe then loueth an other, and is not content with him. And thus we can ſhew you an infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of other ſuſpitions and cares that are harbored in a iealous perſon. What ſhal we then ſay of his lyfe, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> it is farre more greuous than that of any other
<pb facs="tcp:10967:32"/>
liuing creature. He liueth beleuing, &amp; not beleuing,<note place="margin">The miſerie of a iealous life.</note> and ſtill alluring the woman: and moſt times it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that theſe iealous perſons doe ende their liues thorowe the ſelfe ſame malice, wherof they liue fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and not without cauſe, for that with their repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, they ſhewe the way to their owne harmes. Conſidering then the aforeſayde reaſons, more cauſe hath your friende that is iealous to ſorrow, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue<note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Queene vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fift question.</note> you, bicauſe you may hope to get, &amp; he liueth in feare to loſe that which he ſcarſly holdeth for his owne. And therfore if he haue more cauſe of griefe than you, and yet comfortes him ſelfe the beſt he can, muche more ought you to comfort your ſelfe, and to ſet aſide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailings that are more méete for faint heartes: and hope, that the aſſured loue which you beare towards your Lady, ſhal not loſe his due deſert: For though ſhe ſhew hir ſelfe ſharpe towards you at this preſent, it can not be but that ſhée loueth you, bicauſe that loue neuer pardoned any loued to loue: and ye ſhal know, that with the fierce vehement windes are ſooner broken the ſtubbourne okes, than the conſenting réedes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10967:32"/>
               <head>¶ The ſixt Queſtion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by a yong Gentlewoman.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext vnto <hi>Clonico</hi> ſate a faire Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apparelled in blacke veſture vnder an honeſt veile, who as ſhe perceyued the Quene to haue made an end of hir words, thus began to ſaye: Moſt gracious quene I remembre, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a litle girle, how one day I w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who was a propre yong man and of ripe yeares, abode all alone in a garden, without other company: and in tarying there together, it happened that two<note place="margin">Two da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels amorous of a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof: and that which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened.</note> yong damſels of noble bloud, abounding in riches, &amp; borne in this our Citie, who loued this my brother very well, and perceiuing him to be in the ſayde gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, came thyther, and began a farre off to beholde him that was altogether ignoraunt of their purpoſe. And after a while, ſeyng him all alone, ſauing for me of whom they reckned not, bicauſe I was but a little one, thus the one began to ſay to the other. We loue this yong Gentleman aboue all others, neyther doe knowe whether he loueth vs or no, yet is it méete that he loue vs both: ſo that now it is léeful for vs to ſatiſfie our deſire: and to knowe whether he loue ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vs, or whether of vs he beſt loueth, to the ende
<pb facs="tcp:10967:33"/>
that ſhe, whome he ſhall beſt like of, may after remain his, without being hindred of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other: wherfore ſince he is all alone, &amp; that we haue a méete time offred, let vs runne vnto him, &amp; eche one imbrace and kiſſe him, that done, he ſhall take whether of vs beſte pleaſeth him. Theſe two yong Gentlewomen being thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined vpon this reſolution, began to runne their race towardes my ſayde brother. Wherat he maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led greatly, eſpying them, and ſeeing in what ſort they came: but the one of them or euer ſhe came at vs, by a good waye, ſtayed all baſhfull, and almoſt wéeping ripe: the other runne thorowe, and came vnto hym, whom ſhe imbraced and kiſſed, and ſo ſate hir downe by him, recommending hir ſelfe vnto him. And he, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the admiration conceyued of hir boldeneſſe, was ſomewhat ceaſſed, prayed hir as euer ſhe loued hym, to tell him truly what moued them thus to doe? She concealed nothing from him, the which hée hearyng, and examining well in his mynde that which the one and other had done, knewe not how to perſuade hym ſelfe, whether of them beſt loued him, neyther yet whether of them he might beſt loue. And ſo hapnyng at that time to depart from them, he after prayed cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of many of his friendes touching this matter: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath any one euer ſatiſfied his deſire touching y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> demaunde. For the which cauſe (I praye you) from whome I aſſuredly beleue to haue a true definition of this my queſtion, that ye will tel me whether of theſe two damſels ought ſooneſt to be loued of the yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To this Gentlewoman the Quéene thus made aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer:<note place="margin">The aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the Queene.</note> Truly of the two yong women, ſhe as it ſemeth loued your brother beſt, and ſooneſt ought to be loued
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10967:33"/>
of him againe, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> (doubting) baſhfully abode without imbracing him, and why I thus thynke, this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the reaſon: Loue (as we knowe) maketh thoſe alwayes<note place="margin">Loue is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with feare.</note> fearfull in whome he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth abide: and where he is of greateſt force, there is likewiſe the greateſt feare: and this hapneth, bicauſe the intent or conſent of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon loued can not be fully knowen. And if it could be knowen, many things ſhould be done, that in fearing to offende, are lefte vndone, bicauſe the one knoweth that in diſpleaſing, is taken awaye euery occaſion to be loued: And with this feare and loue ſhamfaſtneſſe is always accompanied, and not without reaſon. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>returning then to our queſtion. Wée ſay, that it was an act of one vnfainedly enamoured, that of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomans, whereby ſhe ſhewed hir ſelfe both feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and baſhfull: And that of the other, was rather the part of one both leude and licencious. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he being of hir beſt beloued, ought the rather (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our iudgement) to loue hir beſt. Then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Gentlewoman: Moſt curteous Quéene,<note place="margin">The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth to the Queene.</note> it is true, that where loue abideth with moderation there fear and baſhfulneſſe doth altogether frequent, but where he doeth abounde in ſuch quantitie as he taketh away the ſight from the moſt wiſe (as is alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſaid) I ſay, that feare hath there no place, but that the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of him that féeleth the ſame, are according to him that vrgeth them forwards, and therfore that Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeing hir deſire before hir eyes, was ſo hotly kindled, as al ſhamfaſtneſſe aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>doned, ſhe ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſtraight to him, by whom ſhe was ſo veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked forwardes, as till then vnable to abyde. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not ſo muche inflamed, obſerued the amorous
<pb facs="tcp:10967:34"/>
termes, being baſhefull and remayning behinde, as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. So that then ſhe that ran, loued moſt, &amp; moſt ought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be loued againe. Diſcrete Gentlewoman,<note place="margin">The Quene to the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth anſwer.</note> (ſayd the Quéene) true it is, that exceſſiue loue taketh away the ſight, and euery other due perſeuerance in things that are ought of his nature, but not in thoſe that belong vnto him, the which as he increaſeth, ſo grow they. Then howe greater quantitie of loue is found in any one, ſo much the more feare (as wée ſaid at the firſt) is there alſo founde. And that this is true the cruell heart of <hi>Biblis</hi> doth manifeſt the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Biblis.</note> vs, who howe much ſhe loued, was ſéene by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quele therof. For ſhe ſeing hir ſelf abandoned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, had not the audacitie to diſcouer hir ſelfe with hir propre wordes, but writing ſhe diſcloſed hir vnſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting deſire. Likewiſe <hi>Phedra</hi> many times gaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt<note place="margin">Phedra and Hippolito.</note> to go to <hi>Hippolito,</hi> to whom ſhe thought bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſpeake, and to tel how much ſhe loued him: but the wordes ſhe had to vtter, no ſooner came into hir mouth, but they ſtayed vpon hir tong and there died. Oh howe fearefull is the perſone that loueth? Who<note place="margin">Alcides.</note> hath ben more mightie than <hi>Alcides,</hi> to whom ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied not y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> victorie of humaine things, but alſo he gaue him ſelfe to beare vp the heauens, and not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding was laſtly ſo enamoured, not of a woman, but of a yong wenche, a ſlaue, which he had gained, as fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hir commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, did lyke an humble ſubiect or ſeruant, euen the very baſeſt things. Alſo Paris in<note place="margin">Paris.</note> what he durſt not attempt neyther with eye nor tong, with his finger in the preſence of his loue, wryting firſt hir name with wine that had ben ſpilt, wrote af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I loue thée. How farre paſſing all theſe doth <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiphe</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:10967:34"/>
bring vs a due exaumple of feare, the which<note place="margin">Paſiphe.</note> without any reaſonable intendement, yea &amp; without vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, durſt not ſo much as expreſſe hir deſire to a beaſt, but with hir propre handes, gathering the ſoft graſſe, endeuoured hir ſelf to make him benigne vnto hir, oftentimes decking hir ſelfe at the glaſſe for to pleaſe him, and to kindle him in the like deſire that ſhe was in, to the ende he might attempt to ſeke that which ſhe durſt not demaunde. It is not méete for a<note place="margin">Shame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth the honour of Ladies.</note> woman enamoured, neither for any other, to be pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt and ready, foraſmuch as the great ſhamfaſtneſſe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which ought to be in vs, doth remaine as the guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our honour. We haue the voyce among men, (and the trouth is ſo) to know better how to hide the amorous flame than they do, and nothing elſe engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth this in vs, but the gret feare, the which doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occupie our forces than thoſe of men. Howe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hath there ben of them (and peraduenture we haue knowen ſome) which many times haue cauſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to haue bene bidden, to the ende thereby they might haue atchieued to the amorous effects, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which willingly woulde rather haue bidden the bidder, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he them, if due baſhefulneſſe and feare had not detained them: and not only that, but euery time that No, is ſcaped their mouthe, they haue had in their mindes a thouſande repentyngs, ſaying from their hearts a thouſand times Yea. There remaineth then the like ſcelerate fire on the behalfe of <hi>Semiramis,</hi> &amp;<note place="margin">Semiramis and Cleopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra.</note> 
                  <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> the which loued not, but ſought to quiet the rage of their wanton willes, and the ſame beyng quieted, they after reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred not them ſelues the one of the other. Wiſe marchauntes vnwillingly doe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture
<pb facs="tcp:10967:35"/>
at one time all their treaſures to the haſard of Fortune, and yet notwithſtanding, they care not to graunt hir ſom ſmal portion, the which if they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to loſe, yet doe they féele no griefe of minde at all<note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Queene v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſixt question.</note> for the ſame. The yong woman therfore that embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced your brother, loued him but a little, and that little ſhe committed to Fortune, ſaying: This Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if I may hereby get him, it is wel: but if he refuſe me there ſhall be no more but let him take an other. The other that abode all baſhefull, foraſmuch as ſhe loued him aboue all others, ſhe doubted to put ſo great loue in aduenture, imagining leſt this peraduenture ſhuld diſpleaſe him, &amp; he ſo refuſe hir, that hir griefe ſhould be then ſuch and ſo much, as ſhe ſhould die therof. Let therfore the ſecond be loued before the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The ſeuenth Queſtion, propoſed by GALEONE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Cleare Sunne beame piercing thorowe amongſt the gréene leaues, did ſtrike vpon the aforeſayde Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and did rebound the light therof vpon the faire face of the adorned Quéene who was thereby apparel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with that colour, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s maketh ſhew when as both the children of <hi>Latona</hi> (from vs hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) with their ſtarres onely giueth vs light: and beſides
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10967:35"/>
the ſplendour it brought to hir face, it did ſo lighten the place, as among the freſh ſhade it yelded a maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous luſter to the whole company. Further what time the reflected raye did extende euen to that place where the Laurell crowne on hir head on the one ſide, &amp; the golden treſſes on the other, dyd determine: It ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termingled there among with twinings, not artificial as at the firſt ſight one woulde haue ſayde, that there had iſſued forth amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the gréene leaues a cleare flame of a burning fire, which did ſpread in ſuch ſort, as the aburne haires wer eaſily ſéene to the ſtanders about. <hi>Galeone</hi> that was peraduenture ſooner or better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares of this maruellous ſight tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of the reſt (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet in circle ouer againſt the Quéene deuided only with the water) did very intentiuely behold the ſame almoſt as though he cared for nothing elſe: ſo that he moued not his mouth to the queſtion that was nowe come to his turne: To whome the Quéene therfore (hauing now both kept ſilence a good ſpace, as eke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented the witty Gentlewoman) thus ſayd: The on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire peraduenture of the thing which thou behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, ſtayeth thée: Tell what is the occaſion that hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thée thus appalled, as in following the order of the reſt thou ſpeakeſt not? It is onely (as we beleue) y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> gazing at our head, as if ye had neuer ſéene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame before: Tell vs firſt, and after as the other haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, euen ſo propound you. At this ſodain voice <hi>Galeone</hi> lift vp his mind replete with ſwéete though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſomwhat comming to him ſelfe, as what time he is wont to do, that thorow a ſodain feare doth breake his golden ſléepe, and thus ſayde: Moſt noble and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noumed Quéene, whoſe worthineſſe it ſhoulde be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
<pb facs="tcp:10967:36"/>
for me to declare, my minde was ſo wrapped in gracious thoughtes (when as I did ſo firmely loke at your heade, as in beholding the bright raye, ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the freſhe fountaine, and rebounding vpon your face, me thought there iſſued forth of the water, a little ſprite ſo gentle and gracious to ſée vnto, as he plucked my minde backe, to behold that which he did, and perceiuing peraduenture, my eyes altogither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient to beholde ſo great a ioy, he mounted by the cleare raye into your eyes, and there for a good ſpace made maruellous myrthe, adorning the ſame with a newe cleareneſſe: And after mounting more high, I ſawe how he aſcended by this light (leauing his foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteppes in your eyes) vpon your crowne, where as he together with the raye, kindled (as it ſéemed vnto me) a newe flame, ſuch a one as was of yore ſéene by <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naquil</hi> to appeare to <hi>Seruius Tullus</hi> a little boye, whileſt he ſlept, and ſo went about your crowne, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping from ſprigge to ſprig, like a litle amorous birde, that ſinging doth viſite many leaues, mouing youre hartes with ſundry ieſtures, ſometimes wrappyng &amp; hiding him ſelfe therein, beyng more merrier euery time he came forth therof, &amp; therwith (as it ſéemed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me) ſo iocund in him ſelfe, as nothyng more, &amp; that ſinging, or with a ſwéet voice he vttred theſe words:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of the third rolling Skie, the benigne babe deuine</l>
                  <l>I am: enamoured ſo, to neast in theſe two eyen,</l>
                  <l>That doubtleſſe die I ſhould, were I of mortall route:</l>
                  <l>From twig to twig I twine to feede this my delight,</l>
                  <l>Theſe golden Treſſes whirling in and out:</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe, inflaming my ſelfe, right</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:10967:36"/>So as with flame I ſhew, theffect, the potent might<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of my dartes deuine, piercing where I goe,</l>
                  <l>Eche one wounding, that with ſweete ſight,</l>
                  <l>Doth gaze hir in the eyes: whereas eche houre loe,</l>
                  <l>If ſuch hir pleaſure be, I there deſcend adowne,</l>
                  <l>For of my kingdomes she, Quene is of great renowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>And herewith he ſayd much more, goyng about as at what tyme ye called me, and ye had no ſooner ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but that he ſodenly retired into youre eyes, the which ſparklyng like to the mornyng ſtarre gaue a newe light that made all the place to ſhine: ye haue now heard with what ioy new thoughts haue ſtayed me for a time. <hi>Philocopo</hi> and the reſte maruelled not a little hereat, and turnyng their eyes towardes their Quéene, ſaw that, which to heare ſemed to them impoſſible. And ſhe that was attired with humilitie, liſtned to the wordes that were truly reported of hir, and abode with a ſtable countenance makyng no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere at all. And therfore <hi>Galeone</hi> ſpeaking in this wyſe, followed with hys Queſtion: Moſte gracious Quéene, I deſire to know whether a man ought to be enamoured for his delight or no? And to demaunde this, many things moue me, both ſéene, heard, &amp; held, thorowe the ſundry opinions of many. The Quéene behelde <hi>Galeone</hi> a good while in the face, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, after a certaine ſigh, thus made anſwere. It is conuenient we ſpeake againſt that which with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire we ſéeke to follow. And truely that which you in aſkyng, do propound in doubt, ought to be very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt vnto you. In anſwering you therfore there ſhal be kept y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> begon order. And he whoſe ſubiects we are,
<pb facs="tcp:10967:37"/>
pardon vs the words, that we, as conſtrained thorow force of Iudgement, ſhall (more ſooner than willing) ſaye againſt his diuine maieſtie, leaſt thereby his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation do fall vpon vs. And you that lykewiſe as well as we are his ſubiecte, with a bolde minde giue eare vnto them, neither do you for all that chaunge your purpoſe at all. And to the ende that ſo much the better, &amp; with a more apparant intendine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our words may be receiued, we will ſomewhat digreſſe from our matter, returning again thervnto as briefly as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble we may, &amp; thus we ſay: Loue is of thre ſortes, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which thrée all other things ar loued, ſome tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vertue of one, &amp; ſome thorow the power of an other, according as is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thing loued, &amp; likewiſe the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: The firſt of the which thrée is called honeſt loue: This is the good, vpright, and loyall Loue, the which of all perſons ought to be receiued: This, the high &amp; firſt creator holdeth, linked to his creatures, and them he tieth therewith vnto him. Thorowe this, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, the worlde, Realmes, Prouinces, and Cities do remain in their ſtate: Thorow this we do merite to be eternal poſſeſſors of the celeſtiall kingdom: And without this is loſt all that we haue, in power of wel doing. The ſeconde is called Loue for delight: And this is he, whoſe ſubiectes we are: This is our God, him we do worſhip, him we do pray vnto, in him doe we truſt, that he may be our conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation, and that he fully may bring our deſire to paſſe: Of this is put the queſtion, whervnto we ſhall duely anſwer. The third is Loue for vtilitie, of this loue the worlde is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed more than of any of the other things. This is coupled with Fortune, whileſt ſhe tarieth, he likewiſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:10967:37"/>
abideth: but if they parte, he is then the waſter of many goodes. And to ſpeake reaſonably, he ought to be déemed rather hate than loue. Nowe as touching the propounded queſtion, we nede to ſpeake neither of the firſt, nor of the laſt: we will ſpeake of the ſeconde, that is, of Loue for delight, to whome truely, no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone that deſireth to leade a vertuous life, ought to ſubmit him ſelfe, bicauſe he is the depriuer of honors, the bringer of troubles, the reueler of vices, the copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous giuer of vaine cares, and the vnworthy occupier of the libertie of others, a thing aboue all things to be held moſt deare. What is he then regarding his own wealth (being wiſe) that will not flie ſuch a gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Let him that may lyue frée, following thoſe things that do euery way increaſe his libertie, and let vicious gouernours gouerne vicious vaſſals. I did not thinke, ſayd <hi>Galeone</hi> then, to giue occaſion tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe theſe my wordes to the leſſning of this our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, nor to diſquiet the regiment of our Lord Loue, neither yet to trouble the myndes of any others, but did rather imagine (you defining it according to the intent of me and many others) that ye might thereby confirme thoſe that are his ſubiectes with a valiaunt mynde, and inuite thoſe which are not, with as gréedy appetite: but I ſée that youre intent is all contrary to myne, bicauſe you with your wordes do ſhew to be iij. ſortes of Loue, of the which thrée, the firſt and the laſt I conſent they vs (as you ſay) but the ſecond, the which anſwereth to my demaund, ye ſay it is as much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be fled: As I holde opinion, it is as the increaſer of vertue to be followed of him that deſireth a glorious ende, as I beleue to make apparaunt vnto you by this
<pb facs="tcp:10967:38"/>
that followeth. This Loue, of whom we reaſon (as i<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> maye bée manifeſt to all the worlde, bicauſe wée proue it) doth work this propretie in humaine hearts, that after it hath diſpoſed the mynde to a thing which pleaſeth, it ſpoileth the ſame of all pride &amp; of all fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, makyng them humble in eche doyng, as it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt vnto vs by <hi>Mars,</hi> whome we finde, that in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Venus,</hi> became of a fierce and ſharpe Duke in battaile, a moſt humble and pleaſant Louer. It makes the gréedie and couetous, liberall and curteous. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea</hi> the moſt carefull hider of hir arte, after ſhe felt his flames, liberally yelded hir ſelfe, hir honour and hir artes to <hi>Iaſon.</hi> Who makes men more diligent to high attemptes than he? And what he can do, beholde by <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Menelaus.</hi> Who furthereth forwardes the angry fiers more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth he? He ſheweth vs how oftentymes the anger of <hi>Achilles,</hi> was quieted tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the ſwéete prayer of <hi>Polixena,</hi> He aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers maketh men couragious and ſtrong. Neither know I what greater example may be giuen vs, than that of <hi>Parſeus,</hi> who for <hi>Andromaca</hi> made a marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous proufe of his vertuous force. He dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth al them that are by him apparelled, with excellent qualities, with ornate talke, with magnificence, and with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauntneſſe. He I ſay beſtoweth vpon all his ſubiectes fineneſſe, and gentleneſſe. Oh how many are the good thinges which procede fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him? Who moued <hi>Virgill?</hi> Who <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>de?</hi> Who the other Poets to leaue of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues eternall fame in thoſe their holy verſes, the which (if he had not bene) ſhould neuer haue comen to our eares, but he? What ſhal we ſay further of his vertues? but that he was able to giue ſuch a ſwéete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:10967:38"/>
to <hi>Orpheus</hi> harpe, as after that he had called to that ſound all the woodes, ſtanders about, and made the running ſtreames to ſtay, &amp; to come into his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in milde peace the fierce Lions togethers, with the faint hearted Hartes, &amp; all other beaſtes: he made likewiſe the infernall furies quiet, and gaue reſt and ſwéeteneſſe to the troubled ſoules, and after al this the ſounde was of ſuch vertue, as he attained to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine his loſt wife. Then is he not the chaſer away of honour as you ſay, neyther the giuer of vnſitting troubles, nor the prouoker of vices, nor the diſpoſer of vaine cares, nor the vnworthy vſer of the libertie of others. So y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> euery one of whom he maketh none ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, and is not as yet his ſeruaunt, ought with all their wit and diligence, to endeuour and to occupy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues in the attaining the fauour of ſuch a Lord, and to become his ſubiect, ſince through him he becommeth vertuous. That which pleaſeth the Gods, and men of greateſt ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, ought likewiſe to pleaſe vs. Let ſuch a Lord therfore be loued, ſerued, and liue alwayes in our myndes. Greatly deceiueth thée thine opinion ſaid the Quéene, and it is no maruell, bicauſe as farre as we vnderſtand, thou art ſo far enamoured, as none the like, and without doubt the iudgement of the ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured is méerely falſe, bicauſe as they haue loſt the ſight of the eyes of their minde, ſo haue they baniſhed reaſon as their vtter enimy. And for this cauſe it ſhall be conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we againſt our wil ſpeake of Loue, the which greueth vs, ſince we be his ſubiects. But yet to plucke thée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine error we ſhall turne our ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to a true report, and wil therfore that thou know, that this Loue is nothing elſe, than an vnreaſonable will
<pb facs="tcp:10967:39"/>
ſprong of a paſſion thorowe wanton pleaſure, that is opened to the eyes, nouriſhed with idleneſſe, by the memorie and thoughts of fooliſh myndes: and many times in how much it multiplieth, it taketh away the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of him in whom it abideth, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> things neceſſary, &amp; diſpoſeth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame to things vnprofitable. But bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thou thorow exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple giuing doſt endeuor thy ſelfe to ſhew y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> all goodneſſe &amp; all vertue doth procede fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, we will procede to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> diſproufes of thy proufe. It is no part of humilitie vniuſtly to bring to a mans ſelf, that which belongeth to an other, but rather an arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie and an vnſitting preſumption: The which thing <hi>Mars</hi> (whome thou makeſt thorowe loue to become humble) aſſuredly vſed in taking away from <hi>Vulcan, Venus</hi> his moſt lauful wife. And without doubt this humilitie that appeareth in the face of louers doth not procede of a benigne heart, but taketh roote from guile and deceipt, neither makes this loue the couetous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall, but when as ſuch abundance as thou layeſt to haue bene in <hi>Medea,</hi> doth abounde in the heart, and doth depriue the ſame of the ſight of minde, and moſt fooliſhly is become prodigall of things heretofore du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed deare, and not giuing the ſame with mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but vnprofitably caſting them away, beleueth to pleaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; diſpleaſeth. <hi>Medea</hi> nothyng wiſe of hir pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digalitie, in ſhort time repented very much without vtilitie, and knew that if ſhe had modeſtly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vſed thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir dere gifts, ſhe ſhould not haue comen to ſo vile an ende. And that ſoliciting that purchaſeth or worketh hurt to the ſoliciters, as it ſeemeth to vs, ought not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ways to be ſought for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for much better it is to ſtand idle, than worke harme, although that neither the one
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:10967:39"/>
nor the other is to be prayſed. <hi>Paris</hi> was a ſolicitour to his owne diſtruction, if he behelde the ende of his ſoliciting. <hi>Menelaus</hi> as reaſon was, became diligent, not for loue, but to recouer his honor loſt, as eche diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete perſon ought to doe. Neither yet is this loue a meane to mitigate anger, but the benignitie of mind, the br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt being paſt that induceth it, makes it to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come nothing, &amp; remitteth the offence againſt whome it is angry. And yet louers and diſcrete perſons were wont at the prayers of the perſone loued, or of ſome friende, to forgiue offences, to ſhew them ſelues cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous of that which coſte them nothyng, and to make the crauers therof beholdyng vnto them. And in this ſort <hi>Achilles,</hi> many times ſhewed him ſelfe to expell from him this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geled anger. Likewiſe it ſéemes that this makes men couragious and worthy: But therof I can ſhew you the contrary. Who was a man of gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter valour than <hi>Hercules,</hi> and yet being enamoured became vile and forgetfull of his force, ſo that hée did ſpin thréede with the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Iole?</hi> Aſſuredly in thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wherin occurreth no daunger, a moſt hardy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are the enamoured, and wherin daunger hapneth they ſhew them ſelues in apparaunce hardy, and put them ſelues forward, neither doth loue, but little wit allure them ſo to do, to the ende they may after haue glory in the ſight of their loues, although it hapneth very ſeldome, bicauſe they doubt ſo much the loſyng of the perſon loued, that they are rather content to be helde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le &amp; of little courage, than to giue them ſelues to perill. And yet we doubte not, but this Loue repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all ſwéetneſſe in <hi>Orpheus</hi> harpe. We agrée that it is true that thou haſte ſhewed, that truely in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="tcp:10967:40"/>
loue ladeth the tongs of his ſubiects with ſuch a ſwéeteneſſe, &amp; with ſo many enti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ements<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times would therby make the ſtones turne vp ſide downe, ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> to entice is not only the propretie of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering and inconſtant men, but of vile men. Howe ſhall we ſay, that ſuch a lorde ought to be followed, thorowe the good propretie of the follower? Aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he (in whom he abideth) maketh wiſe and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble counſels to be deſpiſed. For it was euill with the <hi>Troians</hi> that thoſe of <hi>Caſſandra<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> were not heard of <hi>Paris.</hi> He maketh likewiſe his ſubiects to forget and deſpiſe their good fame, the which ought to remayne to vs all on earth after our deathes, as an eternall heire of our memorie. And how much theſe aforſaid did contemne, the ſame <hi>Aegiſtus</hi> maye ſuffiſe for an example: Although <hi>Scylla</hi> wrought no leſſe hurt tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Paſiphe.</hi> Is not he the occaſion that breaketh ſacred bondes of the promiſed pure faith? Yes truely what had <hi>Ariadna</hi> done to Duke <hi>Theſeus,</hi> wherby conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating the matrimoniall bandes, and giuing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his promiſed faith to the windes, he ſhoulde abandon hir poore miſer among the deſert rockes? A little pleaſure in gaſing in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> eyes of <hi>Phedra,</hi> was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to celerate ſo much euill, and of ſuch requitall for the receiued honor. In him alſo is found no law: and that it is true, may be ſene by the doings of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus,</hi> who hauing receiued <hi>Philomena<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> from hir pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull father, and carnally knowen hir, made no ſtay to contaminate the moſt holy lawes matrimonially co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracted betwene him and <hi>Progne,</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomena.</hi> This alſo calling and cauſing himſelf to be called a God, occupieth the reaſons of the gods. Who
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:10967:40"/>
could euer fully w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> words ſhew the iniquitie of him? He to ſpeake briefly, leadeth them that follow him to all euils: and if by happe his followers do any ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous act (which happeneth very feldome) with a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious beginnyng they beginne it, deſiring thereby to come very quickly to the deſired end of their lothſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m willes, the which may be rather ſayd vices, than ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, forſomuch as that is not to be héeded only which man doth, but with what minde it is doone, and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will of the worker, to repute the ſame vicious or vertuous, bicauſe that neuer of an euill roote ſprang a good trée, nor from an euill trée good fruite. This Loue then is leude and naught: and if he be naught, he is to be fled. And who y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> flieth things euill, of conſequent foloweth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he good, and ſo is both good &amp; vertuous. The beginning of this loue is none other thing than feare, the ſequele is ſinne, and the ende is griefe and noy, it ought then to be fled, and to be reproued, &amp; to feare you to haue him in you, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is violent, neither knoweth he in any of his doings to vſe meaſure, and is altogether void of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. He is without al doubt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> deſtroyer of the minds, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhame, anguiſh, paſſion, griefe, &amp; plaint of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame, neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenteth that the heart of whom that lodgeth him be without bitterneſſe, who will then praiſe that he is to be followed, but fooles. Truly if it were lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful we would willingly liue without him, but of ſuch an harme we are to late awares, and therefore it is conuenient for vs, ſince we are caught in his nettes; to follow his life vntil what time as that light which guided <hi>Aeneas</hi> out of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dark waies flying y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> perillous fiers, may appeare to vs, &amp; guide vs to his pleaſures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10967:41"/>
               <head>¶ The eight Queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by a faire Gentlewoman named POLA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of <hi>Galeone,</hi> was ſet a fayre Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whoſe name was <hi>Pola,</hi> pleaſant, and yet vnder an ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt couerture, who after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quéene ble<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, thus began to ſaye: O noble Quéene, ye haue domed at this preſent, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought to folowe this our Lord Loue, &amp; I for my part conſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto: but yet ſince it ſéemes to mée impoſſible, that the youthfull race both of men and women ſhould be runne ouer without this benigne Loue: I gather, at this preſent, ſetting apart (by your leaue) your ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that to be enamoured is léefull, taking the euill doing for due working: And in following the ſame, I deſire to know of you, whether of theſe two wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <note place="margin">Of what degree one ſhould choſe his louer.</note> ought rather to be loued of a yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both two plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him alike, either ſhe that is of noble bloude, and of able kinſefolke, and copious of hauing much more than the yong man, or the other that is neither noble nor riche, nor of kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>folkes ſo abounding as is the yong man? To whom the Quene thus made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: Faire Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, admitting the caſe that<note place="margin">The Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aunſwer.</note> both man and woman ought to follow Loue as you
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:10967:41"/>
haue before affirmed, we giue iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; that in how much the woman is richer, greater, and more noble than the yong man, of whatſoeuer degrée or dignitie he be of, euen ſo ſhe ought to be rather preferred to the loue of a yong man, than ought ſhe that hath any thing leſſe than he: bicauſe mans mynde was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to follow high things. And therfore he muſt ſéeke rather to aduance than any ways to imbace him ſelf. Further there is a common prouerbe, which ſayth:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>The good to couet better tis,</l>
                  <l>Than to poſſeſſe that bad is.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Wherfore in our iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thou art better to loue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> moſt noble, &amp; with good reaſon to refuſe the leſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaid pleaſant <hi>Pola<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Noble Quéene, I would haue giuen an other iudgement (if it had ben to mée)<note place="margin">The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinion of Pola with hir reaſons.</note> of this queſtion, as ye ſhall heare. We all naturally doe rather deſire ſhort and briefe, than long and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous troubles, and that it is a leſſe and more briefe trouble to get the loue of the leſſe noble, than of the more noble, is manifeſt. Then the leſſe ought to be followed: for as much as the loue of the leſſe may be ſaid to be alredy wonne, the which of the more is yet to get. Further, many perills may folow to a man lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a woman of a greater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, than him ſelf is of, neither hath he laſtly therby any greater delight, than of the leſſer. For we ſée a great woman to haue many kinſfolkes, and a great family, and them all as diligent héeders of hir honour, to haue an eie vnto hir, ſo that if any one of them happen to eſpie this loue, therof may folow (as we haue already ſayde) great perill to the louer, the which of the leſſe noble can not ſo lightly come to paſſe: and theſe perils eche
<pb facs="tcp:10967:42"/>
one (as he is able) ought to flie, for as much as who that receiueth harme is ſure therof, &amp; who that hath done it, la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gheth him after to ſcorne, ſaying he ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth well, where he liketh, there let him loue: yet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he more than once. But how<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that once hapneth, where, and for what occaſion, beſides eche one ought to take good héede: it is very credible that a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman will lightly eſtéeme of him, for that ſhe will deſire to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e one more noble or greater than hir ſelf and not one inferiour to hir ſelfe: wherby ſeldom or neuer, he ſhal attaine his deſire. But of the leſſer ſhal happen the contrary, bicauſe that ſhe will glory to be loued of ſuch a louer, and will endeuour hir ſelfe to pleaſe him, to the ende to nouriſhe Loue, and yet if this were not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the power of the louer onely myght be able without feare to being to paſſe to fulfill his deſire. Wherfore I gather, that the leſſe noble ought to be preferred in loue before the more noble. Youre iudgement deceiueth you (ſayde the Quéene) to the faire Gentlewoman, bicauſe Loue is of this nature that how much y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> more one loueth, ſo much the more he deſireth to loue: And this maye be ſéene by them,<note place="margin">The Quenes olution vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the eight question.</note> that thorowe Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e féele the greater griefe, the which although it trouble them not a little, yet loue they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually the more: Neither doeth any one from his heart, although he make great apparance in wordes, deſire therof a ſpéedie ende. Then as ſmall troubles are ſought for of the ſlouthefull, of the wiſe, things that are attained with moſte trouble, are helde moſt deare and delightful. And therfore in louing the leſſe woman, to get hir, ſhuld be (as you ſay) little trouble, and the loue both little and ſhort, &amp; ſhould be folowed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10967:42"/>
as though one in louing would deſire to loue leſſe &amp; leſſe, which is contrary to the nature of Loue, as we haue ſayd. But in louing the greater, that is gotten with trouble, happeneth the contrary: bicauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that as in a thing dearely gotten, with trauaile is repoſed all diligence to the well héeding of the gained Loue, euen ſo is ſhe euery houre the more loued, &amp; the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger doth continue the delight and pleaſure thereof. And yet if ye will ſay that all the doubte is of their kinſmen, we wil not deny it, for this is one of the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. Wherfore, it is a trouble to haue the loue of one of theſe great women: But notwithſtandyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcrete in ſuch caſes procéede by a ſecrete way. And we doubt not but that the honor both of the greateſt and meaneſt woman is by ſome of their kinſfolkes according to their power loked vnto, in ſuch ſort, as a fole may come to an euill aduenture, louing aſwel in a baſe, as in a noble ſtock: But what ſhall he be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The cruelty of Piſistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> will paſſe <hi>Piſiſtrato</hi> in crueltie, hauing offended the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which loued his without forethinking that which he ſhould afterwardes haue done to thoſe that had had the ſame in harte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In ſaying alſo, that louing a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter woman then himſelfe, he ſhall neuer bée able to come to the ende of his deſire, bicauſe the woman coueteth to loue one greater than hir ſelfe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will make of him no eſtimation at all, ye ſhewe your ſelfe to be ignorant that the meaneſt man (in<note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest man of better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition than the noblest woman.</note> what belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to natural vertues) is of greater and better condition, than the nobleſt woman of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. Whatſoeuer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe then deſireth, ſhe deſireth him y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is of greater and better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition than hir ſelf, bicauſe the vertuous or vicious life maketh many tymes the
<pb facs="tcp:10967:43"/>
meane great, and the great meane. In as much ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as any woman ſhall bée ſolicited by any man in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue ſorte, euen ſo without doubt ſhe ſhall yeld to his deſire, though the great with more trouble, than the meane. For we ſée the ſofte water with a continuall fall to breake and pierce the hard ſtone: and therfore let none deſpaire to loue. For ſo much goodneſſe ſhall follow him that loueth a greater woman than hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">The Quene concludeth that we ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loue the more noble woman than the leſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> as he ſhall endeuour him ſelfe to pleaſe hir, to haue decent qualities, the companie of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſonages, to be ornate of ſwete talk, bolde in enterpriſes, and ſplendant in apparell, and if he ſhall attain to greater glorie, the greater delight ſhall he haue of minde, likewiſe he ſhall be exalted with the good report of the people, and reputed of a noble mynde. Let him therefore followe the moſt noble, as we haue already ſayd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:10967:43"/>
               <head>¶ The ninth Queſtion propoſed by FERAMONTE, Duke of <hi>Montorio.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Exte vnto plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant <hi>Pola</hi> ſat <hi>Fera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te</hi> duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torio,</hi> who after the Quéene had ſayde, thus began: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente that it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to loue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye haue alredy fully an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hir queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And that a man ought to loue rather a more noble woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> than a leſſe noble than hymſelf, may very wel be yelded vnto thorow y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſundry reſons by you ſhewed touching the ſame. But foraſmuch as there are ſundry Gentlewome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſundry ſorts attired<note place="margin">Whether is to be choſen in louing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the wife, the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, or the maide.</note> with diuerſities of habites, that (as it is thought) do diuerſly loue, ſome more, ſome leſſe, ſome more hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſome others more luke warme. I deſire to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande of you, whether of theſe thrée, a yong man to bring his deſire to a moſt happy ende, ought ſooneſt to be enamoured of, either of hir that is maried, or of the maide or of the widow? To whome the Quéene made this aunſwer: Of the thrée, the one, that is the<note place="margin">The Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes anſwere.</note> maried woman, oughte in no wiſe to bée deſired, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is not hir own, neither hath libertie to giue hir ſelfe to any: and therfore either to deſire hir, or to
<pb facs="tcp:10967:44"/>
take hir; is both to commit an offence againſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine lawes, as alſo againſt the lawes naturall and poſitiue, the offending wherof, is to heape vpon our ſelues, the diuine anger, and by conſequent, heauie Iudgement. Howbeit, who that gropeth not his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſo farre inwardly, doth oftentimes ſpéede bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in louing hir, than of any of the other two, either maide or widowe, in as muche as he (although ſuch loue ſometimes be with greate perill) is to haue the effect of his deſire. And why this loue may diuers ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes bring the louer to his deſire, ſooner than the loue of the others, this is the reaſon: It is manifeſt, that in how much more the fyer is blowen, ſo muche the more it flameth, and without blowing, it becommeth dead. And as all other things thorowe much vſe doe decay, ſo contrarywiſe luſt the more it is vſed, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> more it increaſeth. The widow in that ſhe hath ben a long time without the like effect, doth féele the ſame almoſt as though it had neuer ben, and ſo is rather kindled with the memorie therof, than with any concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at all: The mayde that yet hath no ſkill thereof, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knoweth the ſame but by imagination, deſireth as it were one luke warme: and therfore the maried woman kindled in ſuch paſſions doth more than any of the others deſire ſuch effectes. What time the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried are wont to receiue from their huſbands oultra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious wordes or dedes, wherof willingly they would take reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge if they might, there is no way left more redier vnto them, than in deſpite of their huſbandes to giue their loue to him, by whome they are allured to receiue the like. And although it be expedient that ſuch maner of reuenge be very ſecrete, that no ſhame
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:10967:44"/>
grow thereby, neuertheleſſe are they yet content in their myndes. Further the always vſing of one kind of meate is tedious: and wée haue oftentimes ſéene the delicate meates left for the groſſe, turning after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vnto the ſame againe, what time the appetite hath ben ſatiſfied of the others. But bicauſe (as wée haue ſayd) it is not lawfull thorowe any vniuſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to deſire that which is an other mans, we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll leaue the married to their huſbandes, and take of the others, wherof a copious numbre our Citie doeth ſet<note place="margin">The widow is to be loued before the maide.</note> before our eyes. And we wold in beſtowing our loue rather ſéeke the widows than the rude maides, groſſe for ſuch a miſterie, and that are not without greate trouble (the whiche in widowes néedeth not) made able to a mans deſire. Further if maydes loue, they knowe not what they deſire, and therefore they doe not follow with an intentiue mynde, the ſteps of the louer as do the widowes, in whom now the antique fier taketh force, &amp; maketh them to deſire that which thorowe long abuſe they had forgotten: ſo that to come to ſuch effect, they (to late) bewéepe the loft ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and the ſolitarie long nightes, the which they haue paſſed in their widowiſh beds. Theſe are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (as it ſéemeth vnto vs) rather to be loued of them in whome is the libertie to ſubmit them ſelues to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, than any of the reſte. Then aunſwered <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramonte:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinion of Faramonte:</note> Moſte Excellent Quéene, what ye haue ſayde of the maried, I had determined in my minde that ſo it ought to be: and now hearing the ſame fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, I am the rather aſſured thereof. But touchyng the maides and widowes, I am of the contrarie opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, bicauſe (ſetting the maried aparte, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:10967:45"/>
by you alleaged) it ſéemeth vnto me, that the maide rather than the widow ought to be deſired: for as much as the loue of the maide ſéemeth more firme and aſſured than that of the widow. For the widow without doubt hath already loued one other time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and hath ſéene and felt many things of Loue, &amp; knoweth what ſhame may follow therof: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore knowing theſe things better than the maide, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth faire and ſoftly: and doubting and not louyng firmely, deſireth now this &amp; now that, and knoweth not to whether for hir moſt delight and greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to linke hir ſelfe, for ſometimes ſhe wil neither the one, nor the other: ſo that deliberation doth wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in hir mynde, neither is the amorous paſſion able to take there ſtabilitie: but to the maide theſe things are altogether vnknowen. And therefore as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuadeth<note place="margin">The conſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie of maides in loue.</note> hir ſelfe with good aduiſement, that of many yong men ſhe greatly pleaſeth one, ſo without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther examination ſhe maketh choiſe of him as of hir louer, and to him onely diſpoſeth hir loue, not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing how for his pleaſure to ſhew any contrary act, neither is there for the more ſure tying of the louer, any newe deliberation by hir ſought forth, touching hir loue, ſo that ſhe is then pure at the will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of him that ſimply pleaſeth hir, and quickly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth hir wounded heart him onely to ſerue as lord. The which thing (as I haue already ſayde) hapneth not of the widowe, &amp; therfore is the other, the rather to be followed. Further, with more efficacie y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> maide tarieth thoſe things that neuer any one of hir ſorte hath ſéene, heard, or proued. And yet ſhe deſireth more to ſée, heare and proue them, than who that hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:10967:45"/>
tymes both ſéene, heard and proued them, and this is manifeſt. Emong the other occaſions for the which our life doeth greatly delight vs, and is deſired to be long, is for to ſée newe things, ſuch as we haue yet neuer ſéene before. And alſo for to ſée thyngs moſte new we haue a great delight to runne with a dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pace to that, which we aboue all other things do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour our ſelues to flie, that is death, the laſt ende of our bodies. The maide knoweth not that delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full coniunction, thorow the which we come into the worlde, and yet is it naturall to euery creature tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe a deſire to be drawen thervnto. Further ſhe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times hath heard from them, that know what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner a thing it is, howe much ſwéeteneſſe doth conſiſt therin, the which with wordes haue giuen fier to the deſire, and therfore drawen of nature, and of a deſire to proue the thing, of hir not as yet proued, doth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the wordes which ſhe hath hearde, deſire boldly with a kindled heart this concourſe. And with whom is it preſumed to be had but onely with him, whome ſhée hath already made lorde of hir mynde? This heate ſhall not be in the widowe, bycauſe hauing once proued and felte what maner a thing it was, ſhe is thereby prouoked thereunto: So that the maide then ſhall loue more, and be more diligent (thorowe the reaſons aforeſaid) to the pleaſure of hir Louer, than the widowe. To what ende ſhall we then wade any further in ſéeking that the maide ought not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">The Quenes ſolution vpon the nynth queſtion.</note> to be loued than the widow? You, ſaid y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Quene reaſon well, and very well you defende your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But yet we wil ſhew you with apparant rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, howe you likewiſe ought to holde the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb facs="tcp:10967:46"/>
that we hold of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention, if with a ſtraight eye ye loke to the nature of Loue. Thus in the Maide as in the widow, &amp; ſo in the widowe as in the Maide we ſée him to be firme, ſtrong, and conſtant, and that this is true. <hi>Dido</hi> and <hi>Adriana</hi> with their doings haue left vs an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aumple. And where as this loue is neither in the one nor the other, none of the aforſaid operations will therof folow. Then is it conuenient that eche one of them doe loue, if we will haue that to follow, wherof both you and I haue alredy talked. And therfore in louing either maide or widow, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out going about to ſéeke whether of them doth moſt diſcretely enamour (as we are certain of the widow)<note place="margin">Maides ought not to loue, but in reſpect of mariage.</note> we ſhall ſhew you how the widowe is more diligent to the pleaſure of the louer, than is the maide. For doubtleſſe among thoſe things, that a woman eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth deare aboue the reſt, is hir virginitie: and this is the reaſon, bycauſe therin conſiſteth all the honor of hir following life. And without doubt ſhe ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſo much vrged forwardes to loue, as ſhe ſhall not willingly be courteous therof, but yet to him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to whome ſhe beleueth to be coupled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as wife, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the matrimoniall lawe. And therfore we go not about ſéeking for this: for there is no doubt but that who will loue to marry, ought rather to loue the maide than the widowe, bicauſe ſhe ſhall be ſlow and negligent in giuing hir ſelfe to him that loueth hir not (if ſhe knowe it) to that effecte. Further, maides are generally fearful, neither are they ſubtile enough to finde the wayes and meanes, whereby they may take the ſtollen delightes: But the widowe of theſe thinges maketh no doubt at all, bicauſe that ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10967:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hath honorably giuen that which the other ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth to giue, and being without the ſame, doubteth not in giuing hir ſelfe to an other, that token which may accuſe: Whereby afterwardes, ſhe becommeth the more aduenturous, bicauſe (as is ſaid) the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt occaſion that bringeth doubt is not in hir: beſides ſhe knoweth better the ſecrete wayes, and ſo putteth them in effect. In that which you ſay, that the maide as deſirous of a thing which ſhe neuer proued, maye be made more diligent to this than the widowe, that knoweth what maner a thing it is, therof the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Maides do not at the firſt time for their delight, runne to ſuch effect (although the thing that deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, the oftener it is ſéene, heard, or felte, the more it pleaſeth, &amp; the more carefull is euery one to follow the ſame (bicauſe it is then more noyſom than pleſant to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This thing wherof we reaſon, doth not folow the order of many other things, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> once or twice being ſéene, are afterwards no more deſired, but rather the oftener it is put in effecte, with ſo much the more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection it coueteth to returne, and more deſireth he y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thing whom it pleaſeth, than doth he whom it ought to pleaſe, and hath not as yet taſted therof. Wherfore the widowe foraſmuch as ſhe giueth leaſt, and is beſt able to giue, ſhe ſhall be the moſt liberall, and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> more ſooner tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the maide, that muſt giue the deareſt thing ſhe hath. Alſo the widow ſhal be ſooner drawn (as we haue ſhewed) than the maide to ſuche effects. For the which occaſion, let the widowe be rather loued than the Maide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10967:47"/>
               <head>¶ The tenth Queſtion, propoſed by ASCALIONE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that <hi>Aſcalione,</hi> who in circle ſat next vnto the Duke <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramonte,</hi> ſhuld now propound: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thus hée ſayde: Moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Quene I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre that there was heretofore in this our citie a faire and noble Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man left the widow of a worthie huſband, the which for that hir maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous beautie, was of many a noble yong Gentleman beloued. And of thoſe many, there were two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men couragious knightes, eche one in what he could did endeuour him ſelfe to attain hir loue. And whilſt this continued, by chaunce it hapned, that an vniuſt accuſation was brought againſt hir, by certain of hir kinſfolkes, before the Magiſtrate, and after by falſe euidence proued, thorowe the which vntrue proceſſe ſhe was condemned to the fier. But bicauſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the Iudge was perplexed, for that it ſéemed him, as it were, to knowe the vniuſt proufe, he was willing to commit hir life to the Gods, and to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes happe, and ſo tied ſuch a condition to his giuen ſentence, as after the Gentlewoman ſhould be ledde to the fier, if any knight coulde be founde the which
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:10967:47"/>
woulde combate in the defence of hir honor, agaynſt him that would maintaine the contrary, and ſhoulde happe to ouercome, ſhe ſhould then be frée, and if the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, to be burned according to the domed ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.<note place="margin">Two Knigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes amorous of one Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman, did in ſundry wiſe ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w their loue.</note> As the condition was vnderſtoode of hir two Louers, and by chaunce ſooner knowen to the one than to the other: He which knewe the ſame ſooneſt, forthwith toke him to his armour, mounted on horſbacke, and came into the fielde, gainſaying him that would come &amp; maintaine the death of the Gentlewoman. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſomewhat later than the firſt vnderſtode of this ſentence, and hearing how that the knight was already in fielde in hir defence, neither that there was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n place for any other to goe thither in that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, and therfore not knowing herein what to do, became very ſorowfull, imaginyng that thorowe his ſlackneſſe he had loſt the loue of the loued Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that the other iuſtly had deſerued the ſame: &amp; whileſt he thus ſorowed his miſſehap, he bethought him, that if he before any other ſhould go armed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fielde, ſaying that the Gentlewoman ought to dye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo ſuffer him ſelfe to be ouercome, he might thereby cauſe hir to eſcape, and ſo according to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, he put the ſame in effecte. The Gentlewoman hereby eſcaped, and was deliuered from peril. So that then after certaine dayes, the firſt knight went vnto hir, and recommended him ſelfe vnto hir, putting hir in remembrance, howe that hée, to preſerue hir from death, had a fewe dayes paſt, offred him ſelf to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of death, and thankes be to the Gods, and to his forces, he had deliuered both hir and him ſelfe from ſo hard an happe: Whervpon it would pleaſe hir, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:10967:48"/>
to his deſert to giue hir loue, the which aboue all things he had alwayes deſired. Afterwardes with the like prayers came the ſeconde Knight, ſaying that for your ſake I haue haſarded my life, and bycauſe you ſhould not die, ſuffred my ſelfe to be ouercome, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon I haue purchaſed to my ſelfe eternall infamie: wheras I contrarywiſe with incountring your ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and willing to vſe my force, might haue ben able to haue gotten the honor of the victory. The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked eche one of them very benignely, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing them both due recompence for the receyued ſeruice. And now they beyng departed, ſhe abode in great doubt to whether of them ſhe ſhould the rather giue hir loue, to the firſt, or to the ſeconde, and therof prayeth counſell of you, on whether of them ye wold ſay, that ſhe ought ſooneſt to beſtowe the ſame. We<note place="margin">The Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the contrary doings of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Knightes.</note> déeme (ſayde the Quéene) that the firſt is to be loued, and the laſt to be left: bicauſe the firſt vſed force, and ſhewed his aſſured loue in diligent ſorte, gyuing him ſelfe to euery perill, that might happen thorow the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture battaile, euen vnto the death, whereby it myght very well haue folowed, foraſmuch as if ſuch a battail to be done againſt him, had ben as lefull to any of the enimies of the Gentlewoman as it was to the louer, he had ben in perill of death for hir defence: neyther was it manifeſt to him, that one ſhould come againſt him, that would ſuffer him ſelfe to be ouercomen, as it happened. The laſt truely went well aduiſed not to die, neither to ſuffer the Gentlewoman to die. Then, foraſmuch as he put leaſt in aduenture, he meriteth to gaine the leſſe. Let the firſt then haue the loue of the faire Gentlewoman, as the iuſte deſeruer thereof.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:10967:48"/>
                  <hi>Aſcalione</hi> ſayd: O moſte prudent Quéene, what is that you ſay? Doth not one time ſuffiſe to be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note place="margin">Aſcalion contrarieth the Quene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> for well doing, without crauing further deſerte? Truely yes. The firſt is well requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, with being of euery one honoured for the receyued victorie: and what greater rewarde nedeth he than honour the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of vertue? the receyued honour did ſuffiſe for a greater matter than he did. And he that with all his witte came well aduiſed, ought he to be vnrecompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced? and further he to be of euery one euil ſpoken of, hauing nothing leſſe than the firſt holpen the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman to eſcape? Is not the witte to foreſée euery bodily force? Howe ſo? If this man with all his wit came for the ſafetie of the Gentlewoman, ought hée for his deſert to be reiected? God forbid it ſhoulde ſo be. If he knewe not the ſame ſo ſoone as the other, this was not thorow negligence: for if perhappes he had knowen it before the other, he would haue ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to that, which he toke diſcretely for the laſt remedy: wherof, rewarde iuſtly ought to folow, the which re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde ought to be the loue of the Gentlewoman, if rightly ſhe ſée vnto him: and yet you ſay the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. God defende from your mynde (aunſwered the Quéene) that vice come to a good ende, merite the<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſolution <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the x. que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</note> ſame rewarde that vertue done to the like ende meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: but rather in as much as vice deſerueth correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo no worldly deſerte can iuſtly ſatiſfie vertue. Who ſhall denie vs to beleue (although we can not manifeſt the ſame with apparant reaſon) but that the laſt Knight as enuious of the good turne he ſaw pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the other, was moued to ſuch an enterpriſe, to the ende to diſturbe the ſame, and not for the loue
<pb facs="tcp:10967:49"/>
he bare to the Gentlewoman, and yet his deuice fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him. He is a foole that vnder the colour of an eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie doeth endeuour him ſelfe (to the ende to receiue recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) to helpe an other. Infinite are the wayes wherby it is poſſible enough for vs to ſhewe at the firſt with open frendſhip, the loue, that one of vs bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth towardes the other, without ſhewing our ſelues as enimies, and after with coloured wordes to make ſhew to haue profited. That which we haue ſayd may now ſuffiſe you for aunſwere, whome olde age more than any thing elſe, ought to make diſcrete. And we beleue, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> when your minde ſhall haue duely diſgeſted theſe things, ye ſhall not find our iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t guileful, but true, &amp; to be folowed. And ſo ſhe held hir peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The eleuenth Queſtion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by a Gentlewoman, named GRACE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here folowed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hym a Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of cheare very mylde, whoſe name was <hi>Grace,</hi> &amp; aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly the name was conſonant to hir na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e wyth an humble and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt voyce beganne theſe wordes: It is come to my tourne, Oh moſte vertuous
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:10967:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Quéene, to propounde this my Queſtion, the which to the ende the time (that now approcheth to our laſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feaſting, may be ſwetened with the newe beginning thereof) bée onely ſpente in talke, I ſhall briefly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which willingly (if it wer leful for me) I wold paſſe ouer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but yet not to pretermit the limits of your obedience, neither the order of the reſt, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde this: Whether is it great delight to the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ſée his loue preſent, or not ſeeing hir, to thinke amorouſly on hir? My gracious <hi>Grace</hi> ſaid y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Quene, we beleue that muche more delight is taken in thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,<note place="margin">Whether is greater plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ſee the preſent, or to thinke on the abſent.</note> than in beholding: bicauſe in thinking on the thing loued, all y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſenſitiue ſpirites do then graciouſly féele a maruelous ioy, and as it were do content their inflamed deſires, with the delight only of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thought. But this happeneth not in the beholdyng, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> onely the viſible ſpirite féeleth ioy, and the others are kindled with ſuche a deſire that they are not able to endure, and ſo remaine vanquiſhed: and that viſible ſpirite ſomtime taketh ſo great pleaſure, that of force<note place="margin">The iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Queene.</note> he is conſtrained to withdraw him ſelfe back, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vile and altogether vanquiſhed. Then doe wée gather hereof, that greater delight is to thynke than to beholde. That thing which is loued, anſwered the Gentlewoman, how much y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> more it is ſéene, ſo much the more it delighteth: and therefore I beleue, that greater delight bringeth the beholding, than doth the thynking, bicauſe euery beautie at the firſt, pleaſeth thorowe the ſight thereof: and ſo after thorowe the continuall ſight, ſuche pleaſure is confirmed in the mynde, as therof is ingendred Loue, and thoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that ſpring from him. No beautie is ſo much lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb facs="tcp:10967:50"/>
neither for any other occaſion than to pleaſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yes, &amp; to content the ſame. Then in ſéeing they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented, &amp; in thinking to ſée, the deſire increaſeth: ſo that more delight foeleth he that is contented, than doeth hée that deſireth to contente hym ſelfe. Wée may ſee and knowe by <hi>Laodomia</hi> how muche more the preſent ſight tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the abſent thought doth delight,<note place="margin">Laodomia and Prothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilaus.</note> bicauſe wée are to thinke that hir <hi>Protheſilaus</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir thought, neither yet was ſhe euer ſéene diſpoſed to other than to melancolie, refuſyng to decke and apparell hir ſelfe with hir coſtlye gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: The which thing in ſéeing him neuer happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: For what time ſhe abode in his preſence, ſhe was mery, gracious, and alwayes ioyfull, and trimly attired. What more manifeſt teſtimony wil we haue than this, that the gladneſſe is not greater of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight than of the thought? Bicauſe that thorow the exteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our doings, that may be comprehended, which in the heart is hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? The Quéene then, thus made anſwer,<note place="margin">The quenes ſolution of the .xi. que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that the thought is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the looke.</note> Thoſe thinges, both delightful and noyſome, that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche moſt nere to the mynde, bring more annoye, and more ioy, than do thoſe farre off from the ſame. And who doubteth but that the thought abideth in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> minde, and that the minde is not from the eye? al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thorow the particuler vertue of the mynde, they haue their ſight, &amp; that it is conuenient for them by ſundry meanes to render their proportions to the animate vnderſtanding. Hauing then in the minde a ſwéete thought of the loued, in that acte which the thought bringeth, in that together with the thing lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, it ſéemes the louer to be. Then he ſéeth the ſame with thoſe eyes, to whome nothing, no not of a long
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10967:50"/>
diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce may be hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Then he ſpeaketh with hir who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he loueth, and peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture with piteous ſtile telleth the annoyes ſuſtained for hir ſake. Then it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for him without feare to embrace hir. Then doth he according to his deſire maruelouſly glad himſelfe with hir. Then doth he holde her wholly at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the which in beholding happeneth not, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſight onely at firſt taketh pleaſure w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out paſſing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And as we ſay, Loue is timorous &amp; feareful, and in beholding, doeth make the hearte tremble in ſuch ſorte, as it leaueth neither thought nor ſpirite in his place. For many with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g beholding of their ladies, loſe thoſe their natural forces, &amp; remain vanquiſhed: and many not being able to moue, ſtande like poſts,<note place="margin">The effecies of fond amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous lookes.</note> other ſome, in tangling and trauerſing their legges, fall to the grounde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Others therby loſe their ſpeache: &amp; by ſight we knowe many other like things to haue happened, the which all ſhould haue ben very accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to them, to whome (as we haue ſayde) they haue happened, if they had not happened at all, howe then bringeth that thing delight, that ſhall willingly be fled? We confeſſe, that if it were poſſible to beholde without feare, it ſhould be a greate delight. But yet litle or nothing without the thought, the which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the bodily ſighte, pleaſeth very muche. And that that whereof we haue ſpoken may come to paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the thought, it is manifeſt, that, yea, and muche more. For we finde that men with thought haue paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the heauens, &amp; taſted of the eternall peace. Than more delighteth the thought than the ſyght. And if ye ſay that <hi>Laodomia</hi> was melancolie with thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, we doe not denie it, but yet it was rather a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous
<pb facs="tcp:10967:51"/>
than an amorous thoughte, that dyd trouble hir: She as it were a diuiner to hir owne harme, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes doubted the death of <hi>Protheſilaus,</hi> &amp; ſtil was thinking theron, contrary to thoſe thoughts wherof we reaſon, which thorow that doubt coulde not enter into hir, but rather ſorowing thorow this occaſion as reaſon was, ſhe ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wed a troubleſome &amp; heauy loke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The twelfth Queſtion propoſed by PARMENIO.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Armenio</hi> ſat next to thys Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and withoute attendyng further, as the Quéene had lefte, thus began<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Moſt mighty quene I was of long time companyon with a young Gentleman, to whome that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned which I intend to ſhew. He as much as any man could loue a woman, loued a fayre yong Gentlewoman of our citie, gracious, gentle, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rich, both of wealth &amp; parents, &amp; ſhe eke loued him for ought that I (to whom his loue was diſcouered) could vnderſtande. This Gentleman th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n louing hir in moſt ſecrete ſorte, fearing that if it ſhould bée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed, that he ſhoulde no wayes be able to ſpeake
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:10967:51"/>
vnto hir: to the ende therfore that he might diſcouer his intent, and be certified likewiſe of hirs, he tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted no one that ſhould attempt to ſpeake of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: yet his deſire inforcing hym, hée purpoſed ſince that he could not bewray him ſelfe vnto hir, to make hir vnderſtande by ſome other, that which he ſuffred for hir ſake. And bethynkyng hym many dayes by whom he might moſt cloſely ſignifie vnto hir that his intent, he ſawe one day a poore olde woman, wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled, and of an orenge tawnie colour, ſo deſpiteful to beholde as none the like, the which being entred the houſe of the yong woman to aſke hir almeſſe, follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed hir forth of the doore, and many tymes after in like ſorte, and for like occaſion, he ſawe hir returne thither. In this woman his heart gaue him to repoſe his whole truſt, imagining that ſhe ſhould neuer be had in ſuſpicion, and that ſhe might fully bring his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to effect: therfore calling hir to him, he promiſed hir moſt great giftes, if ſhe woulde helpe him in that which he ſhould demaunde of hir: She ſware to doe hir endeuour, to whome this Gentleman then diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered his mynde. The olde woman departed, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a whyle hauyng certified the yong woman of the loue that my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion bare hir, &amp; him likewiſe, howe that ſhe aboue all other things of the worlde did loue<note place="margin">A gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and an olde woman were taken by the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> him, ſhe deuiſed how this yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be ſecretly one euening w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> deſired woman: &amp; ſo he going before hir, as ſhe had appointed, ſhe guided him to this yong gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s houſe, wherin he was no ſooner entred than thorow his miſfortune, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yong woman, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> olde, and he, were all thrée found, &amp; taken togithers, by the brethren of the yong woman, &amp; compelled to tell the
<pb facs="tcp:10967:52"/>
trouthe of that they made there, who confeſſed the whole matter as it was. Theſe brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for that they were the frendes of this yong Gentleman, and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing that he as yet had attained nothing that might redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to their ſhame, wold not do him any harm as they might haue done, but laughing ſayd vnto him in this ſort: Thou art now in our hands, &amp; haſt ſought to diſhonour vs, and for that we may puniſhe thée, if<note place="margin">The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man codem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to lye with the yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and olde wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man eyther of them a yeare.</note> we will, of theſe two wayes ſée that thou take the one, either that thou wilt we take thy life from thée, or elſe that thou lie with this olde woman, and this our ſiſter, either of them one yere, ſwearing faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that if thou ſhalt take vpon thée to lye with either of them a yeare, and the firſt yere with the yong wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that as many times as thou ſhalt kiſſe, or haue to do with hir, as many times ſhalt thou kiſſe &amp; haue to doe with the olde woman the ſecond yeare. And if thou ſhalt take the firſt yere y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> olde woman, looke how many times thou ſhalte kiſſe and touche hir, ſo many times likewiſe, and neither more nor leſſe ſhalt thou do the like to the yong woman the ſecond yeare. The yong man liſtening to the ſentence, and deſirous to liue, ſayde, that he woulde lie with theſe two, two yeares. It was graunted him. But he remained in doubt, with whiche of them he ſhoulde firſt beginne, either with the yong, or with the olde. Whether of them would you giue counſell he ſhoulde firſt, for his moſte conſolation begyn withall? The Quéene, and<note place="margin">The Quene decideth the xij. queſtion</note> likewiſe the whole company ſomewhat ſmiled at this tale, and after, ſhe thus made anſwere: According to our iudgement the yong Gentleman ought rather to take the faire yong woman, than the fowle olde, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10967:52"/>
no preſent good tourne ought to be left for the future, neither y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> euill to be taken for the future good, bycauſe we knowe that we are vncertaine of things to come: and in doing the contrary hereof, many haue alredy ſorowed to late: and if any haue praiſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe herein, not Dutie but Fortune hath therin hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen him. Let the faire therefore be firſte taken. Ye<note place="margin">The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinion of Parmenio.</note> make me greatly to maruell (ſayde <hi>Parmenio,</hi>) ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the preſent good ought not to be lefte for the future, to what end then is it conuenient for vs with a valiant mynde to followe and beare worldly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, where as we maye flie them, if it were not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the future eternall kingdomes promiſed to vs thorowe hope? It is a maruellous thing that ſuch a ſhocke of people as are in the worlde, all moyling to the ende at one time to taſte of reſt, and being able to reſt before trouble, ſhould remaine ſo long while in ſuch an errour, as trouble after reſt were better than before. It is a thing very iuſte (as it ſéemeth to me) after troubles to ſeke reſt, but to deſire to reſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trouble in my iudgement ought not to be, neither can it bring delight. Who then will giue counſell to any, that he lie firſt with a faire Gentlewoman one yeare, the which is the onely reſt and ioy of him that muſt lie with hir, in ſhewyng him after that there muſt folowe ſo great anoy and vnpleaſant life, as he muſt in euery act wherin he abode with the yong wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, haue to do as long with a lothſome old woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Nothing is ſo noyſome to a delightfull life, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre, that after death we ſhall be founde ſpotted. This death returning to our memorie as enimie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our being doth diſturbe vs of all goodneſſe &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10967:53"/>
pleaſure, and whileſt this is remembred, ther can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ioy taſted in worldly things. Likewiſe no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light can bée had with the yong woman, that is not troubled or deſtroyed in thinking and remembryng that it behoueth him to do as much with a moſt vile olde woman, who ſhall alwayes be remaining before the eyes of his mynde. The time that flieth with an ineſtimable wing, ſhal ſéeme vnto him to ouerflie, leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eche day a great quantitie of the due houres: and this mirthe is not taſted, where as infallible fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſorrowe is taried for. Wherfore I would iudge, that the contrary were better counſell, that is, that all trouble, wherof gracious reſt is hoped for, is more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, than the delight, wherof anoy is taried for. The colde waters ſéemed warme, and the dreadfull time of the darke night ſéemed cleare and ſound day, and turmoiles reſt to <hi>Leander,</hi> at what time he went to <hi>Hero,</hi> ſwimming with the force of his armes, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the ſalt ſourges betwene <hi>Seſto</hi> and <hi>Abido,</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> delight that he conceiued to haue of hir tarrying his comming. God forbid then, that a man ſhoulde co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et reſt before trauaile, or rewarde before the doyng his ſeruice, or delight, before he hath taſted tribulation: foraſmuch as if that way (as we haue already ſayde) ſhould be taken, the future annoy ſhould ſo much hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the preſent ioye, that not ioy, but rather annoy, it might be ſayde. What delighte coulde the delicate meates, and the inſtrumentes founded with cunning hande, and the other maruellous ioyes made to <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> the tyraunt bring, when as he ſawe a ſharpe<note place="margin">Dionyſius.</note> pointed ſword hang by a fine thréede ouer his head? Let then ſorowfull occaſions be firſt fled, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10967:53"/>
with pleaſure, and that without ſuſpicion, gracious delightes may bée followed. The Quéene made him anſwere, ſaying: You anſwere in part as<note place="margin">The Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſolution of the .xij. queſtion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining that the yong is to be lyen with before the olde.</note> though we did reaſon of eternal ioyes, for the purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing whereof, there is no doubt but that all troubles ought to bée taken in hande, and all worldly wealth and delight to be left aparte: but at this inſtant wée doe not ſpeake of them, but doe moue a Queſtion of worldly delights, and of worldly annoyes. Whervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we anſwer as we ſayde before, that euery world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delight, that is followed with worldly anoy, ought rather to be taken, than the worldly annoy that tari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth worldly delight: bicauſe who that hath time, and tarieth tyme, loſeth tyme. Fortune graunteth hir goodneſſe with ſundry mutations, the whiche is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be taken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when as ſhe giueth, than to moyle to the ende after turmoiles to get the ſame. If hir whéele ſtoode firme and ſtable, vntill that a man had toiled ſo much as he ſhould nede to toile no more, we would then ſay, that it were to be graunted to take paines firſt: but who is certaine that after the euill may not follow the worſſe, as well as the better that is taried for? The tymes together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worldly things are all tranſitory, and therfore in taking the olde wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, before the yeare be complete, the which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſéeme to waxe leſſe, the yong woman may die, and hir brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repent them of this they haue done, either elſe ſhe may be giuen to ſome other, or peraduenture ſtolne away, ſo that after one euill, there ſhall follow a worſe to the taker. But contrariwiſe, if y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yong wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall be taken, the taker ſhall therby haue his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſo long tyme of him deſired, neither ſhall there af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:10967:54"/>
follow that annoy of thoughte, that you ſay muſt follow therby, bycauſe that we muſt dye is infallible, but to lie with an old woman is a hap able enough w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many remedies to be of a wiſe man auoyded, &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things are to be taken of the diſcrete with this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that eche one whileſt he holdeth, and enioyeth them, he diſpoſe himſelfe with a liberall mynde, when he ſhall bée required to reſtore or leaue them. Who that buſieth himſelf to the ende to reſt, bringeth a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt example that without that he cannot haue reſt: and ſince he therefore taketh troubles to the ende to haue reſt, how much more is it to be preſumed, that if reſt were as ready as is trouble, but that he woulde ſooner take that than thys? Neyther is it to bée thought that <hi>Leander</hi> if he had bene able to haue had <hi>Hero</hi> without paſſing the tempeſtious arme of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſea, wherin after he periſhed, would not rather haue taken hir, than haue ſwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e the ſame. It is conuenient to take Fortunes happes what tyme ſhe gyueth them. For no gift is ſo ſmall, that is not better than a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed<note place="margin">A ſmalle gift in hand is better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a promiſed greater.</note> greater. And as for Future thinges, let reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies be taken, and the preſent gouerned accordyng to their qualities. It is a natural thing to deſire rather the good than the euil, when as equally they concurre, and who that doth the contrarie followeth not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon, but his owne folly. We confeſſe, that after troubles quietneſſe is more gracious &amp; better knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> than before, but yet not that it is rather to bée taken than the other. It is poſſible for wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and fooles to vſe the Counſels both of fooles and wiſemen accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their liking: but for all that the infallible ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is not altred, the which doth gyue vs leaue to ſée
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10967:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that rather the faire yong woman than the lothſome olde is to be taken of him, to whome was made ſuche a choiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The thirtenth Queſtion, propoſed by MASSALINE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aſſaline</hi> the whiche ſate on the right hand of the Quéene, &amp; nexte to <hi>Parmenio,</hi> perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the circle, ſayde in thys wyſe: It is mete that I laſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde my queſtion: And therefore to the ende that I may make the pleaſaunt told ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and the before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouned Queſtions to ſeme more ſwete, I ſhal tel you a ſhort tale worth the hearing, wherin there falleth a queſtion very propre to make an ende withall. I haue heretofore heard ſay that there was in this oure Citie a gentleman, who was very riche, that had to wife an excéedyng faire<note place="margin">A Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman was loued of a Knight.</note> yong Gentlewoman, whom he loued aboue al world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges. This gentlewoman was intierly beloued of a Knight of the ſame Citie, but ſhe loued him not at all, neither cared for him, by occaſion wherof, the Knight was neuer able to get from hir, either good wordes or curteous countenance: and while he thus
<pb facs="tcp:10967:55"/>
liued comfortleſſe of ſuch loue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It happened that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was called to the regiment of a citie not farre diſtant from this of ours. And accordingly he went thither, hauing honorably gouerned the ſame all the time of his abode there: during the which it happened, that there came a meſſanger vnto hym, who after other<note place="margin">The Knight aduertiſed of the death of hir whom he loued.</note> newes thus ſaid: Sir ye ſhall vnderſtande, that the Gentlewoman of our Citie, whome you ſo entierly loued aboue all others, this morning labouring with great griefe to be deliuered of childe dyed, not being deliuered, and was in my preſence, of hir parents ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably buried. The Knight not without great ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, gaue eare to this tale, &amp; with a ſtrong heart en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> telling thereof, without ſhewing any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at all, &amp; to him ſelfe thus ſayd: Ha wretched death, curſed be thy power, thou haſt depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me of hir, whome I loued aboue all others, and whome I deſired more to ſerue, although I knew hir cruell vnto me, than any other worldly wight. But ſince it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hus come to paſſe, that which Loue in hir life time woulde not vouchſafe to graunt me, now<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that ſhe is dead, he can not denie me: That aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if I ſhould die therefore, I will now kiſſe the face of hir being dead, that liuing I loued ſo well. And ſo ſtaying vppon this determination he taried vntill it was night, and then toke one of his ſeruants, whom he beſt truſted with him, and trauailed the dreadfull<note place="margin">The Knight ſeketh his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman in hir graue.</note> darke wayes till at the laſt he came to the Citie: And being entred the ſame, he went ſtraight to the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherin the Gentlewoman was buried: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had comforted his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that he without any feare ſhoulde attende him there, he opened the ſame,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:10967:55"/>
and went therinto, where as lamenting with a pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous plaint he kiſſed the Gentlewoman, and tooke hir in his armes, and not ſatiſfied therwith, he began to féele her here and there, and to put his hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> into hir froſen breaſt among the colde dugs. But afterwards (being become more bolde than was méete) to ſéeke out vnder the riche attire whiche ſhée had on, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete parts of the body, going and féeling with a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hande hither and thither till at the laſt he ſpread the ſame vppon hir ſtomacke, where as with a féeble motion he felt the weake pulſes ſomewhat to moue. He then became very feareful, but yet loue made him bolde, and therfore trying further with a more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hede, he knew that ſhe was not dead: and firſt of all with a ſwete mutation he drewe hir oute of that place, and after wrapping hir in a great mantel (lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſepulture open) he and his ſeruaunt caried<note place="margin">The knight carieth hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lady to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mothers houſe.</note> hir ſecretly to his mothers houſe, where as he coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his ſaid mother, thorowe the power of the gods, that ſhe, neither this, nor any thing elſe ſhould mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to any perſone liuing. He cauſed great fires to be made, to the end to comfort the colde membres<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> loſt forces did not therby returne in due ſort: by occaſion wherof, as one peraduenture diſcrete in ſuch a caſe, willed a ſolemne hote houſe to be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, wherin he cauſed firſt to be ſtrowed many vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous herbes, and after placed the Gentlewoman ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, cauſing hir as it was mete for one in that plight, to be tenderly looked vnto. In the which hotehouſe, after ſhe had for a time made hir abode there, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bloud coagulate about the heart, began thorow the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued heate to diſperſe by the colde vaines, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites
<pb facs="tcp:10967:56"/>
half dead began to return<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to their places: wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vpon the Gentlewoman (no ſooner féeling the ſame) began to call to hir mother, and after to aſke where ſhe was: to whome the Knight in ſtede of hir mother made anſwere, that ſhe was in a very good place, and<note place="margin">Lucina, the goddeſſe of childe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</note> that ſhe ſhould comfort hir ſelfe: She abiding in this ſort, calling vpon the woman <hi>Lucina</hi> for helpe, was as it pleaſed the Gods (aboue all expectation) deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of a fayre ſonne, and therewith of great trouble and peril: wherof remaining diſburdened, and being ioyfull of hir newe borne childe, there were oute of<note place="margin">The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with the Knight, was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of child.</note> hande prouided nourſes, both for the charge of hir, as alſo of hir ſonne. The Gentlewoman nowe after all theſe heauie troubles, returned to hir perfect vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and the newe ſonne was alſo borne to the worlde, before ſhe ſawe either the Knight that thus loued hir, or his mother who was preſt to do hir ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, neither did ſhe ſée any one of hir parents or kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes about hir, for to looke vnto hir: whervpon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come into a cogitable admiration as it were all amaſed, ſayd: Where am I? what a wonder is this? Who hath brought me hither, whereas I was neuer before? To whom the Knight aunſwered: Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman,<note place="margin">The knight declareth to the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman how ſhe was brought into his houſe.</note> maruell not, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort your ſelf, for that which you ſée, hath ben the pleaſure of the gods, and I ſhal tell you howe, and ſo declaryng from the beginning to the ende all that whiche was happened hir, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that thorowe him, ſhée and hir ſonne were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue: By occaſion wherof they were alwayes boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to be at his pleaſure. The Gentlewoman percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing this to be true, knowing aſſuredly that ſhe could not by any other meanes but only by this whiche he
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10967:56"/>
ſhewed hir, be come to the hands of the knight: firſt of al with a deuout voice, rendred thanks to the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Gods, &amp; after to him, offring hir ſelf to be always at his pleaſure &amp; ſeruice. Then ſayd the knight: Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman, ſince ye know your ſelfe to be beholdyng vnto me, I will that in guerdon of my well doyng, ye comfort your ſelfe here in this place, vntill I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from my office, wherevnto it is nowe ſo long ſince that I was choſen, as the date therof is almoſte at an ende. Beſides ye ſhal promiſſe me faithfully ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to bewraye your ſelfe without my licence, eyther to your huſbande, or to any other perſon. To whome the Gentlewoman anſwered, that ſhe was vnable to denie him eyther this, or any other requeſte, and that aſſuredly ſhe woulde comfort hir ſelfe: and ſo by othe made vnto him, ſhe affirmed neuer to cauſe hir ſelfe be knowen without his pleaſure. The Knight ſéeyng the Gentlewoman out of all perill to receyue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, after he had abode .ij. dayes in hir ſeruice, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended hir and hir childe to his mothers charge, and ſo departed, returning to the gouernement of his ſaid office, the which after a little while he honorably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and returned home to his owne houſe and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: where as of the Gentlewoman he was graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly<note place="margin">The knight biddeth the huſbande of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> banquet,</note> receiued. Certaine dayes after his returne, he cauſed to be prepared a great banquet, wherevnto he inuited the huſbande of this Gentlewoman, whome he loued, hir brethren, and many others of hir frends and his: and the bidden gueſtes beyng ſet downe at the table, the Gentlewoman according to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Knight, came apparelled in thoſe garmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and decked with that crowne, ring, and other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb facs="tcp:10967:57"/>
orna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nts (as the vſe was then) wherwith ſhe was buried. And by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of the knight placed hir ſelfe on the one ſide by hir huſband, and on the other ſide by him ſelfe, where as ſhe fed that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, without ſpeaking any word at all. This Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman was oftentymes behelde of hir huſbande, and hir attire and ornamentes alſo: and as it ſemed vnto him, he knew hir to be his wife, and thoſe to be the garmentes wherein ſhe was buried: but yet for that he thought he had buried hir dead into hir ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not beleuyng that ſhe was ryſen againe, durſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e not once giue hir a worde, doubting leaſt ſhe had ben ſome other that did reſemble his wife, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that it were more eaſy to finde one woman, in attire &amp; ornaments like to an other, than to raiſe vp a dead body. But yet for all this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he turned many times towardes the knight, and aſked him who ſhe was. To whome the knight anſwered: Aſke of hir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whome ſhe is, ſor I can not tell, out of ſo vnpleaſant a place I haue brought hir. Then the huſband aſked the wife who ſhe was, to whome ſhe aunſwered: I was brought by this Knight by vnknowen wayes in to this place, to that gracious life, that is of euery one deſired. At theſe wordes there wanted no admiration in the huſbande, but rather the ſame increaſed, and ſo they remained vntill the banket was ended. Then<note place="margin">The knight reſtoreth the gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hir huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande.</note> the Knight l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dde the huſbande of this Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a chamber, and with him the Gentlewoman, &amp; the others lykewiſe that banketted with them, where as they found the Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n faire and gracious ſonne in the nourſes armes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whome the knight deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered into the fathers handes, ſaying: This is thy
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10967:57"/>
ſonne, and giuing him the right hande of his wife, ſayde: This is thy wife, and mother of this childe: ſhewing to him and to the reſt, how it happened that ſhe was brought thither. They all after greate won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, made great ioye, and chiefly the huſbande of his wife, and the wife with hir huſband, of their ſonne. And ſo both two thanking the Knight, returned me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily home to their houſe, many dayes after makyng maruellous ioy. This Knight entreated this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman with that tenderneſſe and that pure faith, as if ſhe had bene his ſiſter, and therefore it is doubted which of theſe two was the greater: either the loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<note place="margin">The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie of the Knight, or the ioy of the huſband was the greater. The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> of the Knight, or the ioye of the huſband, that had nowe gotten againe his loſt wife, whome he reputed as dead. I pray you to ſay your opinion, and what you would iudge hereof? Moſt great (as we beleue) (anſwered the Quéene) was the ioy of the again got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wife, and of hir childe: and likewiſe noble &amp; very great was the loyaltie of the Knight. But for that it is a naturall thing to be glad of the getting agayne of things loſt (neither coulde it otherwiſe be bycauſe it would an other) and ſpecially in the gettyng againe of a thing before ſo greatly loued, with a childe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there coulde not bée made ſo greate ioye, as was conuenient. We doe not repute it to be ſo greate a matter as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o doe that wherevnto a man is of hys propre vertue conſtrained to doe, the which in being loyall cometh to paſſe, bycauſe the being and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loyal, is a thing poſſible. We ſay then, that from whom procedeth the being loyal in a thing ſo greatly loued, that he doeth a moſt great and noble thing in keping loyaltie, and that in a farre greater quantitie
<pb facs="tcp:10967:58"/>
loyaltie doth increaſe in him, than doth ioy in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and thus we iudge. Truly ſayd <hi>Maſſaline<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> moſt renoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Quéene, I beleue it be as you ſay: but yet<note place="margin">The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinion of Maſsaline.</note> it ſemes vnto me a greate matter to thinke, that with ſo great ioy as was in him that had gotten again his wife, there coulde be made compariſon of greatneſſe in an other thing: foraſmuch as greater griefe is not ſupported, than when as thorow death a thing loued is loſt. Further, if the knight were faithful, as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſayde, he dyd therin but his dutie, bycauſe we all are bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the working of vertue: and he that doth that, whervnto he is of dutie bounden, doth but wel, but yet it is not to be reputed for ſo great a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Therfore I imagine, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there may be iudged grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note place="margin">The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſolution vpon the laſt Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</note> ioye than loyaltie. You with your words do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary your ſelfe (ſayde the Quéene) bicauſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought as well to reioyce in the goodneſſe of God in takyng him away, as thorowe the working of vertue: but if the one coulde be in the one caſe, as ſorrowfull as the other could be in the other caſe diſloyall, it might be conſented to your iudgement. To followe the lawes of nature, which can not be fled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is no greate matter, but to obey the poſitiue lawes, is a vertue of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> minde, and the vertues of the minde, both for greatneſſe as for euery other reſpect are to be preferred before bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly workes. And if vertuous workes (making due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence) do ſurmount in greatneſſe euery other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, it may be ſayde, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the hauing ben loyall, dureth alwayes in beyng. Ioye may be turned into ſodaine ſorow, either elſe in a ſhorte ſpace of time become lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing, loſing the thing thorowe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he which it is become mery. And therfore let it be ſayde of him,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:10967:58"/>
that vprightly will iudge, the Knight to haue bene more loyal, than the other mery. Not one there was that followed <hi>Maſſaline,</hi> that had any thing more to ſay, for that they all had now propouned their Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions. The Sunne now in ſetting, lefte the place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete with a temperate aire. By reaſon whereof, <hi>Fia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metta,</hi> moſte reuerent Quéene of this amorous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, raiſed hir on foote, and thus ſayd: Gentlemen &amp; Gentlewomen, your Queſtions are finiſhed: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto (the Gods be thanked) we haue accordyng to our ſmall knowledge, made anſwere, following ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſant reaſoning, than matter of contention. And we know, that much more might haue ben aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered vnto the ſame, yea and in farre better ſorte than we haue done: But yet that which we haue ſaid may ſuffiſe to our paſtime: and for the reſte, let it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine to the Philoſophers of <hi>Athens.</hi> We ſée <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> nowe not to behold vs with a ſtraight aſpect, we féele the aire refreſhed, and know this Feaſt, which we at our comming hither left thorowe the exceſſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heate, to be againe begonne by our companions. And therfore it ſemeth vs good, that we returne to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame: and this beyng ſayd, ſhe toke with hir delicate hand, the Laurell crowne from hir heade, and in the place where ſhe ſate, ſhe laide it downe, ſaying: I leaue here the crowne of my honour and yours, vntil that we ſhall returne hither to the like reaſoning. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thus ſayd: ſhe toke <hi>Philocopo</hi> by the hand, that nowe with the reſt was riſen, and ſo returned with them all to their Feaſt. Thence was heard of al ſides the pleaſant inſtruments, and the aire reſounding of amorous ſongs, no part of the Garden was without
<pb facs="tcp:10967:59"/>
banketting: wherein they all abode merily all that day, euen to the laſt houre: but night being come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and the ſtarres ſhewing forth their light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it ſemed good to the Lady, &amp; to them al, to depart &amp; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the citie, wherein being entred, <hi>Philocopo</hi> takyng his leaue, thus ſayde vnto hir: Moſt noble <hi>Fiametta,</hi> if the Gods ſhoulde euer graunt me, that I were myne own, as I am an others, without doubt I ſhoulde bée preſently youres, but bicauſe myne owne I am not, I can not gyue my ſelfe to an other: Howe be it forſomuch as the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable heart coulde receyue ſtrange fier, ſo muche the more it féeleth thorow your ineſtimable worthineſſe to bée kindled, and ſhall féele al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes and inceſſauntly, with more effect ſhal deſire neuer to be forgetfull of your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe. She tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked <hi>Philocopo</hi> gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this curteſy at his departure, adding that it would pleaſe the Gods quickely to bryng a gracious peace to his deſires.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10967:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
